- You know, high school to college,
ميدوني از دبيرستان به دانشاه
it can be a big transition,
ميتونه يه تحول بزري باشه
especially if you're not from the city,
مخصوصا اه واسه اين شهرم نباشي
so-- so we try to help out with that transition
بنابراين ما سعيمون بر اينه که به شما توي اين انتقال کمک بکنيم
in a number of ways.
به روش هاي متعدد
Wow, that's a real accomplishment.
..واي،اين واقعا يه دستاورده بزريه
Congratulations.
تبري ميم
I mean, you're not in yet, but...
..منظورم اينه که ،شما هنوز به ما ملحق نشدي ولي
no, things are looking pretty good.
نه همه ي داره خوب يش ميره
We dc an all-campus picnic, which is a nice way
ما يه تور دوره محوطه ي دانشاه انجام ميديم که راه خيلي خوبيه
for the incoming students to acclimate themselves
براي دانشجوهاي تازه تحصيل که خودشون تطبيق بدن
to the college.
با دانشاه
For me, the mos! exciting thing about this place is the classes'
براي من،هيجان انيزترين يز درمورد اينجا کلاس هاشه
So you don'! want to go lo college?
س شما تمايلي به دانشاه رفتن نداري؟
You know, I'm not up to date on the course catalog.
ميدونيد،من زياد در مورد فهرست برنامه ها و کلاسها به روز نيستم
One of the great things about this school is, you know,
هکي از بهترين يزها درمورد اين دانشاه اينه که ،ميدوني
you have a campus called New York City.
يه محوطه ي دانشاه داري به اسم نيويورک
Greatest city in the world, they say.
بهترين شهر دنيا،به قولي
I thought your nay was- was interesting.
به نظرم مقالتون جالب توجه بود
A spell-check might be nice on than essays.
يه غلط يابي کلمات ميتونه واسه اين مقاله ها خيلي خوب باشه ها
Planning on taking your boards again?
ميخواين دوباره امتحان تعيين سطح بيرين؟ boards يا college boards) (يه يزي تو مايه هاي همون کنکور ماس
Love those extracurriculars.
عاشق اون فعاليت هاي فوق برنامم
Have you heard about the meal plan?
درمورد برنامه غذايي دانشاه يزي شنيدين؟
Fantastic'
يه دونست
Where do you see things going, you know,
آينده ي روبروتو طوري ميبيني؟ ميدوني
after-after college?
بعد دانشاه ميم؟
Hey!
هي
# Hmm, mm #
با سلام
# My sweet love is gone away #
وقتي که براي انجام زيرنويس اين فيلم ها انجام ميشود اصلا کم نيست
# My sweet love is gone away #
بدون دريافت هي ولي تنها براي يشرفت فرهن ما اين وقت رو براي شما عزيزان ذاشته
# My sweet love is gone away now #
و لحظات خوبي رو براي شما آرزو ميکنيم
- Yours or mine?
مال توِ يا مال من؟
- Mine.
مال منه
You can have it if you want, though.
ولي اه خواستي ميتوني داشته باشيش
- Is that a new shirt?
لباست جديده؟
- Uh, yeah, it is.
اوه،آره جديده
Do you like it?
دوسش داري؟
- Don'! ask me that.
از من يکي نرس
- WM?
واس ي؟
- Because ifs not my job
بخاطر اينکه ديه اين شغل من نيست
to make you feel good about yourself anymore.
که يکاري کنم نسبت به خودت احساس خوبي بکني
# Look at how life has drived away #
Tiptak entertainment
# My sweet love is gone today #
با عشق و آرزوي لحظاتي خوش
# Mm-hmm #
تقديم ميکند
- That'll be all for you?
همش همينه جناب؟
- Hmm? - Anything else?
همم؟ يز ديه اي نيست؟
it
اون نه همينه
- That's a nice shirt.
لباس قشنيه
- Thanks'
مرسي
- Hello?
سلام؟
- Jesse Fisher'?
جسي فيشر؟
- Yeah?
بله؟
- It's your favorite Communist.
کمونيسته مورد علاقت داره بات صحبت ميکنه
- Professor Peter Hoberg?
روفسور يتر هابر؟
- Screw you. I'm not a Communist
ببند زيو من کمونيست نيستما
How you doing?
جوريايي؟
- Oh, you know.
اوه،ميدوني
- Listen, I don't want in lake up too much of your time,
وش کن نميخوام زياد از وقتتو به باد بدم
but here's why I'm calling.
ولي واسه ي اين زن زدم که بم
Ever since I announced that I was packing it in,
از اونجايي که ديه اعلام کردم که دارم بارو بنديلمو ميبدنم
funny, but this whole place has finally decided
بامزست،ولي يهويي کل اينجا بالاخره تصميم رفتن که
that they don'! really hate me after all.
بالاخره بعد عمري بهم بن از من بدشون نمياد
Now, I know Ohio is not as glamorous as New York,
حالا،ميدونم که اوهايو به اندازه ي نيويورک جينيل وينيل نيست
but they're throwing me a retirement dinner thing
ولي دارن برام يه برنامه ي شام بازنشستي يه يزي تو اين مايه ها
at the end of the month,
تو آخر ماه برام ترتيب ميدن
and they asked me to invite any former students
و ازم خواستن که هر دانشجوي قديميمو
that might want to lie and say some nice things about me.
که دوس داره الکي دروغ به و يزاي خوب درموردم برو دعوت کنم
And since you're one of the great liars that I know...
و ازاونجايي که تو يکي از بهترين دروغوهايي هستي که من ميشناسم
- When is it?
کيِ؟
- Weekend of the 25th.
25م آخر هفته
You know, check your schedule.
ميدوني،برنامه هاتو يه ک بکن
- OK!!-
باشه
Checking now.
دارم ک ميکنم
Uh, looks like I'd have to shift some things around, but yeah.
اوه،مثل اينکه يه سري کارارو بايد اينور اونور کنم ولي ،باشه
I'll be there.
نوکرتم هستم ميام
- Hi.
سلام
Look at this.
اينجارو باش
Haw are you?
طوري جير؟
Ah.
.آه
- Jesse. - Yeah, hi.
جسي بله،سلام
- Hi, I'm David. This is Susan.
سلام،من ديويدم ايشونم سوزانه
- Hi. - Hey.
سلام
- Peter warned you that we'd be here?
يتر که بهتون اخطار داده بود که ما اينجاييم؟
- He did. He did, yeah.
داده بود داده بود،دوشواري نداره
We're making him take care of us while we're here.
مجبورش کرديم تا ما اينجاييم بهمون خوب برسه
How was your drive?
رانندي طور بود؟
- It was good, yeah. Pleasant, actually,
خوب بود،آره دلذير اه راستشو بخواين
- Peter, Jesse's here!
يتر،جسي اينجاست
- So it's good to be back?
س خوبه که برشتي؟
- Yeah. Yeah, ifs weird.
آره آره يکم عجيبه
I drove up the hill.
من کل ترو رانندي کردم اومد بالا
I suddenly felt like I was seeing
يهو يه حسي بهم دست داد انار يکي از
an ex-girlfriend or something.
دوست دختراي قديمم ديدم يا همين يزي
- The one that got away. - Exactly.
هموني که ييد به بازي دقيقا
- Zibby loves it here so much,
زيبي خيلي اينجارو دوست داره
she get sad to come home on breaks.
کلي ناراحت بود که ميخواست واسه تعطيلات بياد خونه
- Zibby?
زيبي؟
- Sorry. Elizabeth, our daughter.
معذرت ميخوام اليزابت،دخترمون
a sophomore. - Ah.
دانشجوي سال دوم آه
- She's in the improv group.
توي روه تئاتراي بداهه هم عضوه
We came up to see one of her shows.
ما اومده بوديم که يکي از برنامه هاشو ببينيم
- How was it? - Hilarious.
طور بود؟ آخر خنده
- Uh, filthy but hilarious.
اوه،+18 اينا بود ولي خنده دار بود
- Sc how do you guys know Peter?
خوب،شماها يتر از کجا ميشناسين؟
- He was my camp counselor.
مشاور کم من بود
- No way.
نه بابا؟
- He made us sing pro-union songs around the campfire.
مارو به اين کار واداشت که آهن اتحاد و همبستي دور آتيش کم بخونيم
# You mus! stand up for your brother #
سر اومد زمستون
# So you won't die for the man #
شکفته بهارون.
# Stand up for your brother so you won't die for- #
ل سرخ خورشيد باز اومد و شب شد ريزون
He never writes. He never calls,
هيوقت زن نميزنه هيوقتم يزي واسمون نمينويسه
- Oh, hey.
اوه،سلام
- Let me look at you.
بزار نات کنم بينم
Not bad.
همي بدم نيس
Who's hungry?
کي شنشه؟
- I'm hungry- - okay, let's go.
من شنمه اوکي،بزن بريم
We've got reservations.
جا رزرو کرديم خبرمون
Oh, man, 37 years.
اوه مرد 37 سال شد
Can you believe it?
باورت ميشه؟
Native New Yorker spends 37 years in a county
يه نيويورکي اصيل 37 سال عمرشو تو يه شهرستان
where the tallest building's nine stories.
که بزرترين ساختموناش مغازه هاشن ذرونده
Oh, my.
هي بابا
- How are you feeling about it all'!
حس و حالت يه درموردش؟
- The retirement? - Yeah.
بازنشستي؟ آره
- Oh, I don't know.
اوه،نميدونم
Another year of faculty meetings,
اه يه سال ديه بخوام اين استاد مستادارو ببينم
I'd throw myself off that nine-story building.
خودمو از همين مغازه بلنداي اينجا ميندازم ايين
the admissions game, buddy?
اعتراف بازيت طور يش ميره،رفيق؟
Whoa, is that Professor Fairfield?
واي،اون روفسور فيرفيلده؟
- Yeah.
آره
- Wow, she looks fantastic!
واي،قدر خوب مونده جون داداش
Professor!
روفسور
What is she like? Is she cool?
جورياست؟ آدم باحاليه؟
- She's definitely not warm.
اصلا آدم خون رمي نيست
- I loved her British Romantic lit class.
عاشق کلاس ادبيات رمانتيکش بودم
She was, like, the belt teacher I had here.
يه جورايي يهترين استادي بود که اينجا داشتم
She was, like, the second best teacher I had here.
يجورايي دومين بهترين استادي بود که اينجا داشتم
- Unbelievable.
باورنکردنيه
You are unbelievable.
باورنکردني تو واسه خودت
- What?
ي؟
- Tell her how you feel,
بهش حالتو بو خوب
- Jesse, this is my daughter, Zibby.
جسي اين دخترم زيبيه
. HO)'-
سلام
- Peter, should we follow you?
يتر،بيافتيم دنباله تو؟
- If you think that's wise.
اه فکر ميکني عاقلانست
- And he's like, "I had it up to here with America
بعد اينجوري ميفت که من ديه به اندازه کافي اين آمريکارو تحمل کردم
and its repressive, regressive, fascist, “ whatever.
اينجا کشور سرکوبرايانه و به عقب برشته و فاشيستي شده
- I sound like that'? That's how I sound?
من اينجوري حرف ميزنم؟ واقعا اينجوري حرف ميزنم من؟
- You do. You sound like that
آره دقيقا همينجوري
And he gets up in front of the class.
بعد يهو جلوي همه ي کلاس بلند ميشد
He says, 'I just-l couldn't take it anymore,
و ميفت من ديه نميتونستم اينجارو تحمل کنم
so I picked up my life, and I moved to France."
س زنديمو جمع کردم و نقل مکان کردم به فرانسه
- This is being ludicrously misreported, by the way.
اين قضيه داره به صورت افتضاحي اشتباه تعريف ميشه
- So I raised my hand.
بعد من دستم بردم بالا
I said, 'Wait, wail, wait, wait, wail, Peter.
و فتم،وايسا بينم وايسا بينم يتر
"You're telling us you got so angry at this country
يعني داري بهمون ميي که انقدر از اين کشور عصباني شدي
that you moved to France?"
که نقل مکان کردي به فرانسه؟
And Peter says, "Yeah.
بعد يترم فت آره
Well, I had a Fulbright."
خوب من ميتونستم با اساتيد کشوراي ديه جامو عوض کنم
- Yeah, well, yeah, if I told you
آره،خوب،آره اه منم بتون ميفتم که
what this putz was like when he was here,
اين شل وقتي اينجا بود ه شکلي بود
he'd run out of the room crying.
الان داشت ميدويد ريه کنون ميرفت بيرون
- That's probably true.
احتمالا راسيت ميي
- Well, what were you like when you were here?
خوب،ه شکليا بودي وقتي اينجا بودي؟
- I wan very handsome, wasn't I?
کلي خوشتي بودم،نبودم؟
Am I remembering that correctly?
درست يادمه ديه آره؟
- No, I don't remember that.
نه من که يادم نمياد
But what I do remember is you being a real jerk
ولي کاملا يادمه که آخرهفته ي فارغ تحصيليت
in your parents on graduation weekend.
با خانوادت مثل يه آشغال به تمام عيار بودي
He didn't want to leave.
دلش نميخواست بيخيال اينجا شه
- Ifs true.
راست ميه
And I blamed my parents, weirdly, all four of them.
و منم خونوادمو مقصر ميدوستم الکي،هر هارتاشونو
Like it was their fault college was ending.
انار که تقصير اونا بود که دانشاه داره تموم ميشه
- Don'! do that to us.
تو اينکارو با ما نکن
- No, I won't. - She says that now.
نه نميکنم الان ميه حالا
- So your parents told me you're in the improv group?
خوب،خونوادت بهم فتن که تو تئاتر بداهه کار ميکني؟
- Yeah.
آره
- How's that?
طورياست؟
- We the best I love it
ما يدونه ايم،عاشقشم
- What do you love about it'?
عاشق يشي؟
- Um, I think I love how terrifying it is
اوم،فکر کنم عاشق اينه شم که ه ترسناکه
and haw you have in say "yes" to everything.
و اينکه طوري بايد با همه يز بي بله
- Uh, sorry, what does that moan?
اوه،ببخشيد،اين يعني ي؟
- Ifs, like, the only rule of improv.
اين يجورايي،تنها قانون بداهه وييه
You can never say "no."
تو هيوقت نميتوني بي نه
You have to say "yes" and then add something.
مجبوري بي بله و يه يزي بهش اضافه کني
Like, uh-like, look.
مثلا،اه،مثلا ببين
Um, okay, Mom, you and I
اوم،اوکي مامان منو تو
have been wandering in the desert for days,
ند روزه که توي صحرا سرردونيم
and we're about to die, okay'?
بعد ديه داريم ميميريم ديه،اوکي؟
- OK!!-
اوکي
- Okay, and I say, "Hand me that lemonade, “
اوکي،بعد من يهو ميم اون ليموناد بده بمن
So hand me that lemonade.
س ليموناد بده به من
- Jesus, Susan, hand her the goddamn lemonade.
جون مادرت سوزان،ليموناد بده بهش ديه
- Never mind.
بيخيال
Jesse, hand me that lemonade.
جسي اون ليموناد بده من
Thank you.
دستتون درد نکنه
M mm-
ممم
Sweet, just the way I like it.
شيرينه،دقياقا همونجوري که دوستش دارم
- I nailed this.
استاد اين کارم واسه خودما
- It doesn't make sense.
اصلا معني نميده که
We're in the desert
ما تو صحراييم خبرمون
I mean, where would we get lemonade?
يعني،از کجا ليموناد يرمون مياد يهويي؟
- It's great seeing you guys.
خيلي خوب بود که ديدمتون رفقا
- So what was your major'?
خوب تخصصت تو ي بود؟
- I was English with a minor in history,
انليسي بود،يکمم تاريخ
just to make sure I was fully unemployable.
که ديه مطمئن شم که کلا کار يرم نمياد
- Right. - What about you?
آره تو ي؟
- Drama.
تئاتر
I mean, not officially yet,
يعني،هنوز رسمي نشده
'cause my dad's not totally thrilled with the idea,
بخاطر اينکه بابام اونقدرام با اين ايده هيجان زده نشده
so maybe also art history?
س شايدم تاريخ هنر
- I'm just happy you go to clan occasionally.
بيشتر از اين خوشحالم که تو هداري کلاساتم ميري
I thought maybe you just improvised all day long.
فکر کردم صبح تا شب فقط داري بداهه ويي ميکني
- Nope.
نخير
I mean, I do, I guess.
منظورم اينه که،فکر کنم همينکارو ميکنم
Have you ever thought about that'!
تاحالا بهش فکر کردي؟
- About what?
به ي؟
- How everything in life is basically improvised?
که طور همه ي تو زندي اساسا في البداهست؟
There's no script.
هي نمايشنامه و متني نيست
We're just making this up as we go.
ما همينجوري که ميذرونيم يزارو ميسازيم
- That's true.
راست ميي
- So yeah.
اوه آره
Well, improv is deep, man.
خوب،بداهه اصل جنسه مرد
- Well, we're about in head out - Oh.
خوب،ما ديه داريم ميريم اوه
- Pleasure to meet you, Jesse. - Yeah. yeah. you too.
از ديدنت خيلي خوشحال شديم جسي آره،آره واسه منم
- Take care. Bye.
مواظب باشين خداحافظ
- So I'll- I'll see you around, I guess.
س من... همين دور اطراف ميبينمت بعدا فکر کنم ديه ؟
- Yeah, yeah, see you around. - Okay.
آره،آره همين ورا ميبينمت اوکي
- It was nice to meet you.
خوشحالم شدم ديدمت
- Yeah, you too.
آره،واسه منم
- See you later. - Okay, bye.
بعدا ميبينمت اوکي،خدافظ
. Enjoy college.
از دانشاه لذت ببر
- You wearing a tie tonight'?
امشب کروات ميزني ديه؟
' Huh?
هاه؟
- What can you say, really?
واقعا ي ميتوني بي
People get up and say all this great stuff about you.
همه ميان بالا و اين يزاي خيلي خوب در موردت مين
You know, I'm thinking,
ميدونين،داشتم فکر ميکردم
'Who in the hell are they talking about?"
درمورد کودوم خري دارن حرف ميزنن؟
We just, where does the lime go?
فقط،اين زمان کجا رفت؟
This seems impossible.
اصلا غيره ممکنه
37 years.
37 سال
There comes a time in a man's life
يه وقتايي توي زنديه آدم هست
when it hurts to do the math.
که برا ادم دردناک ميشه که اين رياضيارو انجام بده
You know, I worry that I've been hero so long
ميدونين،من نران اينم که اينقدر که اينجا بودم
that I'll be lousy being anyplace else.
ديه جاهاي ديه بدردنخور باشم
Oh, well, I guess I'll find out very shortly.
اوه،خوب فکر کنم خيلي زود ته و توي قضيه در مياد
Um, hey, thanks for the chicken.
اوم،هي،مرسي بابت مرغ
It was a little cold, but still I...
يکم سر بود،ولي خوب..
Think nice thoughts about me when I'm gone,
وقتي نيستم درموردم فکراي خوب بکنين
if you can.
اه ميتونين
- No, they did it at Macalester.
نه،اون قضيه رو تو مکالستر انجامش دادن
I really think it could work here.
من که واقعا فکر ميکنم اينجام جواب ميده
- Well, it sounds great.
به نظر که عاليه
I tell you, talk about it on Monday.
ببين ي ميم بيا دوشنبه درموردش صحبت کنيم
- Oh, sure.
اوه،حتما
Night, Jesse'
شب بخير جسي
- Yeah, good night.
آره،شب بخير
- It's a good idea, though.
ايده ي خوبيه ها ولي
a terrible idea.
ايده ي افتضاحيه
Oh, what a disaster.
اوه،ه فاجعه اي
- What-no, it was nice
ي؟نه بابا خيليم عالي
- You're not half the liar you used to be.
مصف اونموقع هاتم نميتوني دروغ بيا
You know, it really means a lot to me
ميدوني،واقعا برام خيلي ارزش داشت
that you came out for this.
که تو بخاطر اين قضيه اومدي اينجا
- How could I miss it'?
طور ميتونستم از دستش بدم؟
You're the second best teacher I had here.
تو دومين بهترين استادي هستي که من داشتم
- I'm serious.
جدي ميم
I'm gonna take off.
من ديه ميرم
- Well, I'll come with you.
خيلي خوب،منم بات ميام
- Oh, no, no, no, you slay.
اوه،نه نه نه نه تو بمون
I want to be alone for a bit.
ميخوام يکم تنها باشم
- I feel you, man.
حست ميکنم داداشي
A lot of information in trees.
کلي اطلاعات مطلاعات توي درختا ريخته
- Uh...
اوه
- How's your night going?
شبت جوريا يش ميره؟
- Fine.
خوب
- Is your name.
اسمتو
Ethan?
ايتنه؟
- No. WW!
نه،را؟
- You look like an Ethan to me.
شبيه يه ايتن ميموني واسه من
- My name's not Ethan.
اسمم ايتن نيست
- How cool would that have been if that was your name
قدر خدا ميشد اه واقعا اسمت اين بود
and l just, like...
بعد منم يجورايي ميفتم...
Knew it?
ميدونستم
Are you a student here?
دانشجو مانشجويي اينجا؟
- Uh, no, but thank you tor thinking that.
اوه،نه ولي مرسي که اينطوري فکر کردي
You?
تو ي؟
- Nah, man.
نه بابا
I'm just here visiting a buddy of mine.
فقط اومدم اينجا يکي از رفيقامو ببينم
But it's not a bad place to kill a little time, huh?
ولي يجورايي جاي بديم نيست که يزره علافي بکشي نه؟
I'm Nat.
اسم من نته
- I'm Jesse.
من جسيم
- Do you hear that music, Ethan?
صداي موزيک ميشنوي ايتن؟
It sounds like a celebration.
انار يه جا برنامه مرنامه ايه
I say we do a little sherlocking,
من که ميم يکم شرلوک بازي دربياريم
find out where ifs coming from going on.
ببينيم داره از کجا مياد و ه خبره
- No- - Don't say no.
نه نه نو
Fortune never smiles on those who say no.
شانس هيوقت به اونايي که مين نه لبخند نميزنه
- I would get you a beer, but alcohol's for suckers, man.
يه آبجو برات ميرفتما جون داداش ولي الکل واسه اسکل مسکلاست
- Uh, yeah.
اوه آره
Listen, Nat, this isn't really my scene anymore.
وش کن،نت،اين کارا ديه به فاز من نميخوره
I'm gonna-
...من ميرم که
- Give yourself five minutes to adapt, my brother.
نج ديقه به خودت وقت بده تا جابيفتي بابا داداش
Change is never easy.
تغيير هيوقت آسون نيست
Tell me this.
بو ببينم
What are your thoughts on crop circles?
نظرت درمورد طرحاي دايره اي شکل که تو مزرعه ها ميفته يه؟
- Uh, I don't have any.
اوه،هي نظري ندارم
some seriously weird shit going on, bro.
يه سري اتفاقاي عجيب مجيبي توشون ميفته جون دادا
You think it's just a bunch of drunk English guys
فکر ميکني کار يه مشت انليسيه مست
with planks and rope?
با ردا و ازين حرفاس؟
You're a fool. - Mm-hmm.
تو يه احمقي هممم
- Spend some time with those patterns.
يه زره برو تو کار اون طرحا
You can feel it.
قشن ميتوني حس کني قضيه رو
Somethings trying to communicate with us.
يه يزي داره شعي ميکنه که با ما ارتباط برقرار ميکنه
It should be on the front page of every paper every day.
اين قضيه بايد هر روز توي صفحه اول هر روزنامه اي باشه
- Okay. Thanks.
اوکي مرسي
- Ha?
هي
I thought that was you,
فکر کردم تويي ها
- Hi. - How'd you and up here?
سلام جوري کارت به اينجا کشيده يهويي؟
- He made a friend.
يه رفيق واسه خودش دست و ا کرد داداشمون
- Yeah, yeah, I-yeah
آره،آره...آره
- Look at you.
ناش کن
You're, like, back in college.
انار که،دوباره برشتي به دوران دانشاه
- Whee!
هورا
- How does it feel?
ه حسي داره؟
- Oh, this is Vanessa.
اوه،اين ونساست
- Hey. - Hi.
سلام
- Tm Nat - Hey.
من نتم
- Jesse's an alum.
جسي و خونواده
We had brunch this morning.
امروز صبح باهم ناشتا خورديم
I think my mom has a little crush on him.
فکر کنم مامانم يجورايي رفته تو کفش
- You went here?
شما اينجا دانشا ميرفتين؟
- I did, yeah
آره،بله
- When'd you graduate?
کي فارغ تحصيل شدي؟
- Oh, man, it was, uh, -.
اوه،مرد،دهه ي 90 بود
That was when we were born.
اون موقع که ما تازه به دنيا اومديم
- Yeah, yeah
آره آره
I'm old.
يريم ديه
- But you look good.
ولي به نظر که خوب ميرسي
And you're overdressed.
و ديه زيادي لباسات لوخوريه
- That's better.
بهتر شد
- Why do I like this guy so much?
را من انقدر از اين داداشمون خوشم مياد؟
- Because he's likable.
بخاطر اينکه دوس داشتنيه
gel you guys some drinks.
هي بياين يکم براتون مشروب جور کنيم
- Yeah, no, I think I'm gonna- I'm gonna take off.
آره،نه من فکر کنم که بخوام برم ديه
- No, you should slay.
نه،بايد بموني
- No, really, I should go.
نه،جدي ديه بايد برم
- Do you drink coffee? - Yeah.
کافي ميخورين؟ آره
- What? crazy.
ي؟ خدا شد که قضيه
So does my friend here.
داداشمونم ميخوره
You two, tomorrow.
شما دوتا،فردا
Shoop! Coffee.
اوس کافي
- Yeah, I could do that You want to?
آره،من که ايم،تو ي؟
- Um, I-yeah, uh, yeah.
ام،آره،اوه آره
That'd be-that's great.
خيليم عالي
Oh,
اوه
Oh, you're serious.
اوه،جدي فتي مثکه
Ia 11:30 okay?
11:30 اينا خوبه؟
- Yeah, that works.
آره آره اينم جواب ميده
. HO)'-
هي
- Hi.
سلام
- Can we talk'?
ميشه حرف بزنيم ؟
- Yeah. Yeah, sure, okay.
آره حتما اوکي
See you tomorrow'?
فردا ميبينمت؟
- Yeah, yeah. See you then.
آره آره ميبينمت
- OK!!-
اوکي
- Hey, Vanessa.
سلام،ونسا
- Don'! sweat that guy.
زيادي به اون يارو فکر نکن
She only had eyes for you.
اون شاش تورو رفته بود
- OK!!-
اوکي
Good night, Nat
شب بخير نت
- Good night, Ethan.
شب خوس ايتن
- Can I help you?
کمک نميخواي داداش؟
. Surf!-
شرمنده
I just-
فقط
just the best book of all time.
اين بهترين کتاب کل ادواره
I just like holding it, I guess
فکر کنم فقط دوست داشتم يکم دستم بيرمش
- Best book of all time?
بهترين کتاب ادوار؟
- Well, one of them, sure.
خوب،يکيشون،حتما
- Have you ever noticed how everyone around here
تاحالا به اين توجه کردي که جوري آدما
speaks in wild hyperbole?
اينجا با بيشترين اغراق ممکن حرفشونو ميزنن؟
Everything's the best.
همه يز بهترينه
Like, 'He's the best professor ever, '
مثلا،اين بهترين استاد زمونست
or, "This is the best patty" melt on the planet, “
يا که اين بهترين ساندوي کلوه ايه سيارست
as if they've sampled every possible variety
انار که خبرشون همه ي نمونه هاي
of professor and patty melt,
روفسور و ساندوي کلوه اي رو  امتحانش کردن
which is, as we know, logistically impossible.
که همونجور که ميدونيم منظقي بخواي حساب کني غير ممکنه
- ORGY-
دوشواري داري شوما
- Hey.
سلام
- Am I super lab?
خيلي دير کردم؟
- Uh, no. You wan! a coffee?
اوه نه قهوه ميخوري؟
- No, I'll just drink yours.
نه،قهوه ي تورو بخورم بستمه
- You okay?
حالت خوبه؟
- I don't know yet
هنوز نميدونم
I smell like beer. Do you smell that'?
يجورايي بوي آبجو ميدم بوش ميفهمي؟
- Yeah, actually, you do.
آره راستشو بخواي آره
- I-I need to excuse myself just-
بايد يه لحظه ببخشيد
just for a-
...فقط واسه
- Sorry about that.
شرمنده
Back there.
واسه اونجا
You walked away, and I was just wondering
تو رفتي و من يهويي به خودم اومدم که
why I was being rude to someone who loves the same writer I do.
را داشتم با کسي مثل خودم عاشق يه نويسندست بد حرف ميزدم
And I don'! have an answer for that
و هي جوابيم واسش ندارم
- OK!!-
اوکي
- Okay, so yeah, um,
اوکي،خوب،امم
I'll just-
...من ديه
- My grades tanked senior year.
سال اول نمره هام داغون بود
That book was the only thing I wanted to read.
اون کتاب تنها يزي بود که دلم ميخواست بخونمش
You liking it?
دوسش داري؟
- Uh, yeah.
اوه،آره
It's my second time reading it, actually.
راستشو بخواي اين دومين باريه که دارم ميخونمش
- WWI.
واي
That's impressive.
تاثيربرانيزه
Ifs not short.
داستان کوتاهي نيست
- Yeah, I know.
آره ميدونم
- You know, he said the purpose of fiction
ميدوني،يه جا فته که هدفِ تخيل
was to combat loneliness.
جنيدن با تنهايي بوده
good.
خوب بود
I never heard that.
هيوقت نشنيده بودم
- Yeah.
آره
Well, on the other hand,
خوب،از اونورم
spending most of your time with an 1,100-page book
ذروندن بيشتر وقتت با يه کتاب 1100صفحه اي
tends to put a dent in your social life.
يه جورايي يه وري توي زندي اجتماعيت ايجاد ميکنه
- Yeah.
آره
Loneliness simultaneously increased and decreased.
تنهايي به طور همزمان کم و زياد ميشه
. HO)'-
سلام
- What, you guys know each other?
ي ميي،شماها همديرو ميشناسين؟
- Yeah, we had Symbolic Logic first semester.
آره،ترم اول يه کلاس منطق سمبليک باهم داشتيم
Zibby.
زيبي
- Right. Dean, hi.
درسته دين،سلام
- Hey. - I'm Joan, by the way.
هي منم اسمم جسيه
- OK!!-
اوکي
- Hmm.
هم
Interesting guy.
آدم جالبي بود
- Yeah.
آره
I can'! believe he's even back here.
حتي باورم نميشه که دوباره برشته اينجا
- Why? What do you moan?
را؟ منظورت يه؟
- He had a manic episode last year.
سال يش يه حمله ي عصبي بهش دست داد
Eventually, they look him lo a hospital
آخر سر بردنش بيمارستانُ
and, I don't know, calmed him down, I guess.
نميدونم،آرومش کردن،فکر کنم
He's supposed to be, like, the smartest guy ever.
يجورايي از اوناس که قراره باهوش ترين آدماي دنيا باشه
- Everything okay?
همه ي خوبه؟
- Yeah, everything's great.
آره عاليه
I puked.
من بالا آوردم
- On.
اوه
- That's gross.
حال بهم زن بود حرفم
Sorry, you did not need to hear that
ببخشيد نيازي نبود که اينو بشنوي
Come on, let's-let's walk.
اشو بريم يه راهي بريم
My parents really liked you.
خونوادم کلي ازت خوششون اومده بود
- Oh. nice.
اوه عاليه
I like them.
منم دوسشون داشتم
You're really lucky to have parents like that.
تو خيلي خوش شانسي که يه خونواده ي اين شکلي داري
- Like what?
ه شکلي
- Like, I don't know.
يه شکلي،نميدونم
Around, first of all.
دورو ورتن،اول از همه
Still together so they can fret over you as a team.
هنوز باهمن که بتونن به عنوان يه تيم سرت غر بزنن
- Yeah, I guess.
آره،فکر کنم
I like them best when they're not being so parental,
عاشق اون وقتاشونم که زياد بالاسر بازي در نميارن برام
which is, like, 1% of the time.
که يجواري 1%اوقات بيشتر نيست
Oh, I thought of this great trick
اوه،يه حقه ي خيلي باحال به ذهنم رسيده بود
for having them annoy me less.
که يکاري کنم که کمتر بتونن اذيتم کنن
Want to hear if? - Okay.
ميخواي بشنوي؟ باشه
- Okay, I decided to treat my parents
اوکي،تصميم رفتن با خونوادم يه جوري رفتار کنم
like they're always drunk.
انار که هميشه مستن
No, really, it works.
نه،جدي،جواب ميده
Any time they say something irritating or offensive,
هر دفعه که يه يز آزاردهنده و زشت مين
I'm just like, "Oh, I can't get mad at them.
منم ميم،اوه من که نميتونم از دستشون عصباني بشم
They're drunk. It's not their fault."
مستن ديه تقصير خودشون که نيس
And why should I take advice from drunk people seriously?
و اينکه جدي را بايد از آدماي مست نصيحتم بيرم؟
- That's great.
عاليه
- Do you like classical music?
موزيک کلاسيک دوست داري؟
- Yeah, sure.
آره،حتما
- Okay, I took this music survey claw last year.
اوکي،من يه کلاس موسيقي از واحداي انتخابيم سال يش رفتم
Oh, my God!
خداجون من
It totally changed my life.
کلا زنديم عوض کرد
I'm really happy I ran into you last night
واقعا خيلي خوشحلم که ديشب يهويي ديدمت
- Yeah, yeah, mo too.
آره،آره منم همينطور
Ifs random.
تصادفي بود
Who was that guy?
اون ياروِ کي بود؟
- What guy?
کودوم يارو؟
- The-last night, that guy.
ديشب،اون يارو
- Oh, his name is Eric.
اوه،اسمش اريکه
- Erie
اريک
ls Eric your fella?
اريک معشوقه اينات ميشه؟
- No.
نه
You know, I think I like almost everything about this place
ميدوني فکر کنم من تقريبا عاشق همه يه اينجا هستم
but the dude situation.
غير از وضعيت سراش
- Not great?
خوب نيست؟
- No one, like, dates.
هيشکي قرار مدار ذاشتن دوست نداره
so casual about it all.
انار که اصلا يز خاصي نيست
- Same as when I was here.
دقيقا همونجوريه که من اينجا بودم
- Yeah.
آره
I guess there's part of me that's a little old-fashioned.
فکر کنم يه قسمتايي از من هست که يکم رو مد نيست
- Well, on behalf
خوب،به نمايندي
of all current and former 18- to 22-year-olds,
از تمام دانشجويان 18تا22 ساله
I'd like to apologize.
بنده از شما عذرخواهي ميکنم
Forgive us.
مارو عفو بفرماييد
Seriously.
جدي ميم
We know not what we do.
ما ه نميدونيم ه ميکنيم
- I think one of the things
فکر کنم يکي از يزايي
I loved the most about being here
در مورد اينجا بودن خيلي دوس دارم
was the feeling that anything was possible.
اين حس بود که انار همه يز ممکنه
It's just infinite choices ahead of you.
انار که بي نهايت انتخاب جلوي روته
You'd get out of school, and anything could happen.
از دانشاه مياي بيرون و هريزي ممکنه اتفاق بيفته
And then you do get out, and...
بعد جدي مياي بيرون و
life happens, you know'?
زندي اتفاق ميفته مييري ي ميم؟
Decisions gel made.
تصميما رفته ميشن
And then all those many choices you had in from of you
و همه ي اون انتخابايي که جلوي روت داشتي
are no longer really there.
ديه اونجا نيستن
At a certain point, you just got to go,
از يه جايي به بعد ديه فقط بايد بي
"Oh, I guess this is new its going down.
اوه،فکر کنم  يزا يش مياد ديه
And there's just something a little depressing about that.
و يه يز يکي غم انيز نسبت به اين قضيه هست
- Well, don't you think you're romanticizing youth a bit much?
فکر نميکني يه ذره درمورد جووني داري خيالردازي ميکني؟
You know, 'cause it's just as hard and annoying
ميدوني،بخاطر اينکه دقيقا به همون اندازه که
lo be young an it is to be old, I'm assuming.
جوون باشي سخته و زنندست که ير باشي
Nut that you're old, 'cause, you know, you're not
نه که تو ير باشيا بخاطر اينکه نيستي
- Look, I get the whole “we're all equal" argument,
ببين،باشه کل قضيه ي ما همه مساويم و اينارو رفتم
and it's kind of true, but it's also kind of not true.
و يجواريم درسته ولي يجوراييم درست نيست
Like, okay, I feel different now than I felt when I was here,
مثلا،باشه،من الان که اينجام حسم با اون حسي که يه وقتي اينجا بودم فرق ميکنه
and I hate to break this lo you, but so will you.
و ازينم متنفرم که اينو به روت بيارم ولي توام يه روز همين حس خواهي کرد
- So you're saying things suck?
س داري ميي همه يز مزخرفه؟
I should prepare myself for suckiness?
بايد خودمو واسه مزخرفات آماده کنم؟
- No, a liberal arts education solves all your problems.
نه،يه دانشجوي هنرهاي آزاد تمام مشکلاتتو حل کرده
- Thank God!
خدايا شکرت
- Worth every penny.
هر قرونش ميارزيد
- We should hug.
ما بايد همديرو بغل کنيم
- What?
ي؟
- I mean, we could keep talking,
منظورم اينه که،ميتونيم هنوز حرف بزنيم
but I think it would be better if we hugged.
ولي فکر کنم بهتره که همديرو بغل کنيم
Come on.
زودباش
- Okay.
باشه
Who slam'! - I do.
کي شروع يکنه؟ من ميکنم
- Okay. - Here we go.
اوکي رفتيم که رفته باشيم
God, so you were here a long time ago.
خداجون،س جدي جدي خيلي وقت يش اينجا بوديا
- Whoa, okay.
واو،اوکي ديه
- I mean- - Enough, enough.
....منظورم اينه که بسه،بسه
That's-l mean, l just mean because I thought,
منظور اينه که فقط اين بود که
with the greenhouses”.
با اين قضيه ي خونه سبزا
- Hey, before you go, I thought you might like these,
هي،قبل از اينکه بري فکر کردم ممکنه اينارو دوس داشته باشي
'cause I don't really need 'em anymore and, uh, here.
واسه اينکه ديه بهشون احتياجي ندارم و
Ooh. Look at this one.
اوه اوه اينو ناه
Huh? No?
هاه؟ نه؟
- Nah.
نه
- Oh, please, that's a great shirt
اوه،جون مادرت لباس به اين خوبي
You know the trouble I unused in this shirt'!
ميدوني ه دردسرايي با اين لباس درست کردم؟
- I can only imagine,
تصورشم زياده
- You gut no taste on top of everything else.
هيي که نداري سليقم نداري
Oh, my God, what a beautiful shirt
اوه خداجون عجب لباس خوشليه
Not giving it to you anyway. - All right
بخوايم بت نميدم ديه خيليم عالي
- Oh, it feels great!
اوه،ه حالي ميده
Hello?
الو؟
Oh, hi.
اوه سلام
No, no, he's-he's still here,
نه نه نه هنوز اينجاس
Yeah, hold on.
آره،صبر کن
Zibby.
زيبي
- Hello?
الو؟
- You haven'! left yet.
هنوز نرفتي
- Uh, no. - Good.
اوه نه خوبه
I need to see you before you go.
قبل از اينکه بري ميخوام ببينمت
Will you meet me at the bookstore?
تو کتابفروشي مياي ببينمت؟
Say yes'
بو آره
- Yea.
آره
ORGY
اوکي
asking about a book I recommended.
داشت درمورد يه کتاب که بهش توصيه ميکردم ميرسيد
- Hmm.
هم
- All right, I'm off. - Okay.
خيلي خوب،من رفتم ديه اوکي
- Be a gentleman. Walk me to my car.
آقا باش و منِ تا ماشينم همراهي کن
- All right, all right.
خيلي خوب خيلي خوب
- Thanks for the shirts. I'll gel them next time, okay?
مرسي بابت لباسا دفعه ي بعد ميام مييرمشون باشه؟
- Yeah, you'll be an the road, and you'll be saying,
آره،تا ميرسي تو جاده ميي
"Oh, maybe I'll call him up.“
شايد بهش زن زدما
- Hey.
سلام
- Sorry, I don't want to hold you up or anything,
شرمنده نميخواستم الکي نهت دارم يه يه يزي تو اين مايه ها
but I, um-
اما اوم
I made this for you.
اينو برات درست کردم
Burned it, whatever,
رايتس کردم،هري
Um, ifs music from the survey class
اوم،موزيکاي اون کلاس موسيقيس
I was telling you about.
که درموردش بهت فتم
- Oh. - Classical, baroque, opera.
اوه کلاسيک،باروک،ارا
- WWI.
واي
This is great.
عاليه که اين
I know none of this.
من هيکودومشو نميدونم يه
Who says we always have to be listening
کي فته که ما هميشه بايد
to obscure indie bands, right'?
به روه هاي منام وش بديم؟
- Right.
درسته
So, um, yeah, I don't know.
خوب،اوم،آره،نميدونم
This is all music I never thought I'd like or care about,
اين همه ي اون موزيکاييه که فکرشم نميکردم هيوقت بخوام دوست داشته باشم يا بهشون اهميتي بدم
and this class just-
...و اين کلاس يهو
well, you know how you can be told something so many limes
ميدوني وقتي يه سري يزارو ممکنه بهت هزار بار ن
and it's like, 'Whatever,"
بعد توام بي باشه بابا
and then you have a great teacher
بعد يهويي يه استاد خوب به ستت ميخوره
take you through it,
و تورو ميبره تو قضيه و
and suddenly it's like, "Beethoven, whoa."
يهويي ميي بتهوون واي
- Yeah.
آره
Thin is really great Thank you.
اين واقعا عاليه،مرسي
I wish I had come with something for you.
اي کاش منم دست خالي نبودم
- Well, you know what you could do?
خوب،ميدوني تو ميتوني يکار کني؟
You could write me a letter.
ميتوني برام نامه بنويسي
- I could do that.
ميتونم اينکارو بکنم
- Handwritten, I mean,
منظورم نامه ي دست نوشتست
like with a pen or something.
مثلا با خودکار يا يه ي تو اين مايه ها
- Ooh. - Yeah, paper.
اوه آره،کاغذ
Maybe seal it with some red wax.
شايد يه مهر از اين موم قرمزام روش بزني
- I could listen to this while I'm writing.
ميتونم وقتي دارم به اينا وش ميدم برات بنويسم
- Right, it'll be like full-on 17th century.
آره،يجورايي ميشه دقيقا مثل قرن 17
- Right, right.
درسته درسته
So, um, I don't have your address.
خوب،اوم،من آدرستو ندارم
- Oh, 108 it my P.O. box.
اوه،کد سيتم 108
And you can figure out the rest, right?
بقيشم که ميتوني بفهمي آره؟
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
آره آره آره
- I also-l put my number on the inside of the case.
من همينطور شمارمم ذاشتم توي جعبه
- Yes, you did.
آره ذاشتي
- You know, in can you ever-
...ميدوني هروقت فازشو
whatever.
هري
- Yeah, right.
آره،درسته
Okay-
اوکي
- Well...
خوب
- Yeah.
آره
Bye. - Bye.
خدافظ
- Professor Fairfield.
روفسور فيرفيلد
Uh, Jesse Fisher.
اه،جسي فيشر
I, um-
من،اوم
I took your British Romantic literature class
کلاس ادبيات رمانتيک انليسرو باتون ذروندم
when I was here as a student.
وقتي دانشجوتون بودم
. And?
و؟
- And I loved it.
و اينکه عاشقش بودم
Great.
عاليه
Hey, Dean.
سلام دين
- I know ifs bad for you.
ميدونم برا آدم بده
- Just quit when you graduate, like everyone else.
فقط مثل بقيه که فارغ تحصيل ميشن ترکش کن
- Sweet ride.
ماشين خوبيه
- You jerk
عوضي
It's a rental.
کرايست
I'm not the best at flying.
زياد با رواز اينا خوب نيستم
- I can understand that
درکت ميکنم
- Where you headed?
کجا ميرفتي؟
- Back to my dorm.
خواباه
- Get in. I'll give you a lift.
سوار شو ميرسونمت
- So you went here, right'?
س اينجا ميرفتي دانشاه آره؟
- I did.
ميرفتم
- You liked it'?
دوسش داشتي؟
- Am.
زياد
I mean, you block out the bad memories-
منظورم اينه که خاطره هاي بدشو از يادت ميبري
writing a senior thesis, February.
يه ايان نامه هم مينويسي،فبريه
- Yeah, February here sucks.
آره،فبريه مزخرفه
- Yeah, it's horrible.
آره،افتضاحه
So other than February, things are good for you here?
س غير از فبريه،همه يز برات خوب يش ميره؟
- I wouldn't say that.
من که همين حرفي نميزدم
- You want to-you can tell me about it if you want.
ميخواي...اه ميخواي ميتوني درموردش برام بيا
Well, um, ifs nut exactly a secret.
خوب،اوم،اين ديه دقيقا يه راز نيست
Last year, I kind of, um lost my mind a bit.
سال يش،من يجورايي يکم عقلم از دست دادم
I don'! really remember much of it,
زياد ازش يزي يادم نمياد
but apparently I got up to some pretty amusing antics.
ولي ظاهرا که کاراي خيلي عجيب غريبي ميکردم
So now they've got me on this pretty heavy stuff,
س حالام يه سري از اين يز ميزاي خيلي سنين بهم دادن
which I guess allows me to function
که فکر کنم بهم اجازه ميده که بتونم کار کنم
but it also makes everything seem underwater,
اما يجورايي يکاري ميکنه همه يز زيرآبي به نظر برسه
which is not an pleasant as it sounds.
که اصلا اونقدر که به نظر ميرسه خوشايند نيست
- Why'd you come back?
را برشتي؟
a nurse.
مامانم يه رستاره
She raised me on her own.
خودش تک و تنها من بزر کرد
I got a full ride.
بورسيه ي کاملم دارم
She's...
اون
so proud I'm here.
خيلي به خودش ميباله که من اينجام
Thanks for the lift.
مرسي بابت سواري
- 'Dear Zibby, I can't thank you enough
زيبي عزيزم،نميتونم به اندازه ي کافي
"for introducing me to this music.
بابت معرفي اين موزيک ازت تشکر کنم
"Beyond just genuinely loving it,
فراتر از اينکه واقعا عاشقش شدم
“I feel it's quietly altering my feeling about New York City,
احساس ميکنم کاملا احساسمو نسبت به شهر نيويورک درون کرده
"with which I've always had
يزي که هميشه يکم
"a slightly conflicted relationship.
رابطه ي متضادي باهاش داشتم
"I've found that if you replace the horns and the shouting
اينو فهميدم که اه جاي بوق ها وفرياد هارو
"with, say, Schubert or Telemann,
با ي مين ،شوبرت و تلمان عوض کني
"the city becomes unbearably beautiful.
اين شهر به نحو تحمل ناذيري زيبا ميشه
"After years of thinly disguised rage on both our parts,
بعد از يه خشونت کويک بوجود اومده ي دوطرفه
"it's like the music has mediated a truce between us
مثل اين ميمونه که اين موسيقي واسطه ي يه قرارداد متارکه ي جن بينمون شده
"Some early favorites.
يه ندتا از مورد علاقه هام که تازه وش کردم
“Massenefs Meditation.
مديتيشنه ماسينيتز
"lf a more beautiful piece of music has ever been composed,
اه واقعا يه موسيقي قشن تر از اينم ساخته شده
"I don't know it.
من که واقعا نميدونم
'That Brandenburg concerto is no joke,
اون قطعه موسيقي براندبور شوخي نبود
"and I echo your sentiment regarding Beethoven.
و جمله ي خودتو درمورد بتهون براي خودت اکو ميکنم
'Whoa.
واي
"I have no idea
هي ايده اي ندارم
"what the Vivaldi piece from Giustino is actually about,
که قطعه ي ويوالدي نواخته شده ي جيويينو درمورد يه
'but to me, it suggests deception,
ولي براي من يشنهاد يه جور تزويز ميده
"some kind of elegant double-crossing.
يجور خيانت ظريف
"It makes me feel like I'm a double agent
بهم اين حس ميده که انار من يه مامور مخفيم
"knee deep in some kind of sexy espionage.
که توي يه جور خبريري شهواني به زانو در اومده
"I've decided the Wagner overture you included
تصميم رفتم که يش درآمد وانر که اين تو ذاشتي
"should come with a warning label.
بايد با يه برسب اخطار روش ميومد
"According to some quick online research,
طبق يه سري تحقيق سري آنلايني که کردم
"the opera deals with the struggle
ارا مبحثش کشمکش
"between sacred and profane love,
بين روحاني و کافر عاشقه
“which is arguably the only struggle there is.
که اه بخوايم روش بحث کنيم تنها کشمکشيه که وجود داره
"The other day, I was crossing the street
يه روز،داشتم از خيابون رد ميشدم
"lost in my head about something,
در مورد يه يزي توي سرم غرق شده بودم
"a not uncommon state of affairs.
يه جور حال غيرمعمول
"I was listening to the overture,
داشتم به يش در آمد وش ميدادم
'and as the music began to swell,
و همونطور که موسيقي داشت برجسته ميشد
"I suddenly realized that I had hands and legs and a torso
يکهو فهميدم که من دست دارم ،ا دارم با يه نيم تنه
"and that I was surrounded by people and cars.
همونجوري که دورم ر بود از مردم و ماشين ها
"It's hard to explain exactly what happened.
خيلي سخته که واقعا توضيح بدي ه اتفاقي افتاد
"But I felt in that moment that the divine,
ولي توي اون لحظه احساس خدايي و الهي بهم دست داد
“however we may choose to define such a thing,
ه بخوايم يه همين يزيرو اينطوري تعريفش کنيم يا نه
"surely dwells as much in the concrete and taxicabs
قطعا سکون همونقدري که توي بتون ها و تاکسي هاس
"as it does in the rivers, lakes, and mountains.
توي رودخونه و درياه و کوه هام هست
"Grace, I realized, is neither time- nor place-dependent.
زيبايي،فهميدم که  متعلق به زمان يا مکان خاصي نيست
'All we need is the right soundtrack
تنها يزي که نياز داريم موسيقيه درسته
"I suppose this new infusion of music in my life is,
فکر کنم اين تزريق موسيقي جديد توي زنديم
"at the very least, making me reconsider
حداقل حداقلش،يه کاري کرد
my hastily to dead, white males."
که تو عجول بودنم واسه رسيدن به نامه هاي مرده ي سفيد تجديد نظر کنم
- 'And I've you to thank for that
و بخاطر اين تورو دارم که متشکرت باشم
"How's things, by the way?
راستي،زندي طوره؟
Your friend, Jesse Fisher.“
دوست تو،جسي فيشر
- "Jesse, things is good,
جسي،همه ي خوبه
'So happy you're loving the music.
خيلي خوشحالم که موزيکارو دوست داشتي
"I felt my whole life got an upgrade
احساس کردم زنديم يه ترقي کامل کرد
"when I took that class.
وقتي اون کلاس رفتم
"The thing that floors me must
يزي که منو خيلي متعجب ميکنه
"is that human beings wrote that music.
اينه که انسان ناطق اين موزيکارو نوشته (اينجا صداش شبيه اخبارو  کانال يک نيست؟)
"Are people writing music like that nowadays?
ديه آدما امروزه روز همين موزيکاييم مينويسن؟
"If they are, I don't know about it
اه مينويسن،که من خبري ازش ندارم
"I hope you've fallen in love with the piece
اميدوارم که عاشق اون قطعه ي
"from Cosi fan tutte.
کوزي فان توته بشي
“I find that when I listen to it, for some reason,
فهميدم وقتي بهش وش ميدم به يه دلايلي
"everyone I see becomes instantly more attractive.
هرکسي رو که دورورم ميبينم يکهو برام جذاب ميشه
Please experiment with it and get back to me."
لطفا يه امتحاني بکن و بهم خبرشو بده
- “Elizabeth, you were right about the Mozart piece.
اليزابت،در مورد قطعه ي موزارت راست ميفتي
“It somehow made everyone in New York lock like
يه جورايي يه کاري کرد که همه توي نيويورک
"a viable romantic partner.
شبيه ارتنراي رمانتيک بادووم شده بودن
"I can't escape it any longer.
ديه نميتونم ازش فرار کنم
"I think I like opera.
فکر کنم از ارا خوشم اومده
"You are never to tell anyone this, ever.
جون مادرت اينو هيوقت به هيشکي نو
Seriously."
جدي ميم
"Your opera secret is safe with me.
رازت ارات يش من در امان ميمونه
“I've been relistening to the music
بعد از هرکودوم از نامه ها
"after each of your letters.
به همون موسيقي وش ميدم
"I like hearing your take and then revisiting them.
از اينکه نظر تورم مييرم و دوباره وششون ميدم خوشم مياد
"And even though Pennsylvania stands between us,
و اره نسيلوانيا بين ما قرار رفته
"knowing we're hearing the same sounds
ولي همينکه ميدوني ما داريم يه صدارو ميشنويم
'makes me feel you are not all that far away.
بهم يه حسي رو ميده که انار ما اونقدرام باهم فاصله نداريم
"If I haven't been clear about this, I miss you.
اه زياد شفاف نفتم حرفمو دلم برات تن شده
"Hmm, don'! really know why.
همم،واقعا هم نميدونم را
"I barely know you.
من به سختي ميشناسمت
"By the way, handwritten letters?
ضمنا،نامه هاي دست نوشته؟
"Greatest thing in the world.
بهترين يز تو دنيان
Keep them coming.“
همينجوري ادامشون بده
- "You asked why music like this isn't being written today.
رسيدي که را موسيقي شبيه به اين امروزه نوشته نميشه
“I wonder if these composers were expressing things musically
در تعجبم اه اين آهنسازا يه جوري اين موسيقي رو ابراز کردن
that are too large for our current psychic state...'
که ديه الان براي حالت روانيه ما خيلي بزره و تو مخمون جا نميشه
- "Anyway, all is fine here.
به هارحال،همه ي اينجا خوبه
College continues colleging along..."
دانشاه دانشاه بودنشو ادامه ميده
- "Massenet's Meditation, for instance,
مديتيشنه ماسينيتز مثلا
'and I worry that my nervous system
و اينکه من نران اينم که سيستم عصبيم
is ill-equipped to contain such immensity of feeling.“
ميتونه يه همين عظمت احساسي رو تو خودش جا بده يا نه
- "I bet if we went here at the same time,
شرط ميبدنم اه ما تو يه بازه ي زماني اينجا ميرفتيم دانشاه
we'd have been great friends."
دوستاي خيلي خوبي براي هم ميشديم
- 'Will this music be the death of me?
آيا اين موسيقي باعث مر من ميشه؟
"If so, you'll have blood on your hands, Elizabeth.
اه ميشه،مقصرش تويي اليزابت
Can you deal with that?“
ميتوني با همين يزي کنار بياي؟
- "Jesse, as much as I love these letters,
جسي،همونقدر که من عاشق اين نامه هام
“I'd like to see you again.
دوست دارم که دوباره ببينمت
"The sooner, the better.
هري زودتر بهتر
“So come back here and see me.
س بررد اينجا و منو ببين
'The dudes here continue to be 18 to 22 years old,
سراي اينجا هنوز 18تا 22 ساله ان
"and they continue to act their age,
و هنوز به اقتضاي سنشون رفتار ميکنن
"I'd like a gentleman caller, and I'd like him to be you.
من از مدل جنتلمنيش خوشم مياد و دوست دارم اونم تو باشي (سکس ميخواد بنده خدا دختره)
Ever yours, Zibby."
هميشه براي تو،زيبي
- "Dear Elizabeth, I've decided to take you up on your offer.
اليزابت عزيز،من تصميم رفتم که همونجوري که يشنهاد دادي بيام يشت
"I'll be getting in on the 14th and slaying at the inn,
من هاردهم ميرسم اونجا و توي يه مسافرخونه ميمونم
but I will be available for walks, strolls, saunters
ولي براي قدم زدن رسه زني و ولردي
"ambles, and promenades.
ردش و رخش در دسترس خواهم بود
'Looking forward to it.
هيجان دارم براش
Jesse Fisher."
جسي فيشر
. HO)'-
اوکي
- So, Bob, um,
ي،باب،ام
I've been asking myself a lot of tough questions lately.
اين ند وقته کلي سوال سخت از خودم ميرسيدم
Everybody knows I made a whole stink
همه ميدونن که من يه کاري کردم که يه سوراخ بوي تعفن بيره
about leaving this place, you know, how it's time-
با اين قضيه ي از اينجا رفتنم ...ميدوني که وقتشه و
- How if you'd look back,
که اه دوباره برردي سر اينکار
you'd tum into a pillar of salt
تبديل به يه ديوار نمک ميشي
- Yeah, all that-
آره،همه ي اينا
- I think I may have spoken too soon.
فکر کنم زيادي زود اين حرفارو زدم
I think-l think I still got a little gas in the tank is all.
فکر کنم فکرکنم هنوز يکم بنزين توي مم دارم
I just-
...من فقط
- Well, Peter, you have no bigger fan around here than me.
خوب يتر،تو هي طرفداري بزرتر از من اينطرفا که نداري
- Thank you.
مرسي
- When you announced your plans, we were all sad to see you go,
وقتي برنامتو به ما فتي ما همه ناراحت بوديم که ببينيم داري ميري
but you insisted that it was time.
ولي تو اصرار کردي که ديه وقتشه
- Right, which I thought it was.
درسته،که فکر ميکردمم هست
- We hired someone,
ما يکي رو استخدام کرديم
young guy out of UVA.
يه سر جوون از دانشاه ويرجينيا
Very impressive candidate.
ه کانديداي خوبي
He was our first choice, actually.
اه راستشو بخواي اولين انتخابمونم بود
We didn't think we would get him, but we did.
فکر نميکرديم که بتونيم بدستش بياريم ولي آورديم
You said you wanted nothing to do with the search.
تو خودتم فتي که اصلا دوس نداري تو جستجوي اين قضيه حضور داشته باشي
- Right, right No, I-
درسته درسته نه،من
I just-
من فقط
I just didn't think it would move so fast.
فقط فکر نميکردم اينقدر سريع ميتونه انتقال يدا کنه
- Well, there was unanimous enthusiasm for the candidate,
خوب،يه اشتياق متفق القول سر اين کانديدا بود
so things just moved along faster than normal.
س يکم سريع تر از بايد انتقال يدا کرد
- Bob.
باب
Give me this one,
اين يکيو بمن بده
- Polar, we can't.
ولار،ما نميتونيم
The department has spent thousands of dollars
دارتمان هزاران دلار سر اين
on this search.
جستجو خرج کرده
He's turned down other offers.
اون بقيه ي يشنهاداشو رد کرده
You know what goes into this sort of thing.
ميدوني که اينجور يزارو جوري بهش رسيدي ميشه
- I hired you, Bob.
من تورو استخدام کردم،باب
You don't have to tell me how this w-
مجبور نيستي بهم بي که اين يزا ....طوري
And let me tell you,
و بزار يه يزيو بت بم
there was not unanimous enthusiasm for you back then.
هي اشتياق متفق القوليم اونموقع ها براي تو نبود
It took a lat of arm-Misting on my part
عرق جبين و کد يمين ريختم که
to gel people to come around.
ملت نسبت به تو نظر خوب يدا کنن
And now, 20 years later, the only reason
حالا بعد 20 سال تنها دليلي که
that you're the chairman of this goddamn department
تو رييس اين دارتمان لعنتي هستي
is 'cause I loathe politics!
اينه که من از سياست بدم مياد
And you, for reasons which I cannot fathom, do not
و تو به دلايلي که من نميتونم درک کنم بدت نمياد
In fact, you seem to have a real taste for it.
راستشو بخواي،به نظر خيليم باب طبعته
Wow'
واي
I'm asking-
خواستم
I'm asking a favor.
يه لطف خواستما
Listen'
وش کن
Just give me this one, Bob, okay?
فقط همين يکيو بهم بده،باب باشه؟
I need three more years.
من به سه سال ديه احتياج دارم
- I'm luff!-
معذرت ميخوام
There's nothing I can do.
هي کاري نيست که من بتونم انجام بدم
- Hey-
سلام
- Oh, hey.
اوه سلام
- Jesse, you remember Vanessa, right?
جسي،ونسارو يادته؟
- Uh, yeah, hi. - You're back'
اوه آره سلام برشتي
- Yeah.
آره
- So I should-
س من بايد
uh, yeah, I got some stuff to do.
اوه آره،من يه سري کار دارم که بايد بهش برسم
- So this is your room.
س اين اتاقته
- Yeah. Fancy, huh?
آره خوشله هاه؟
Forgot how small these are.
يادم رفته بود قدر کويکن
Good training for living in New York
تمرين خوبيه واسه زندي تو نيويورک
- So are you gonna see Professor Hoberg
س روفسور هابرو ميبيني
while you're here?
تا وقتي اينجايي؟
- You know, probably not
ميدوني،احتمالا نه
Um...
ام....
and, you know, if you- if you run into him,
و ميدوني،اه يهويي بهش برخوردي
maybe don't mention that I'm here.
شايد بهتره اشاره اي نکني به اين که من اينجام
. ORGY- - OK!!-
باشه
- Do you want to sit?
ميخواي بشيني؟
- Yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
آره آره آره
So I should tell you,
خوب اينو بايد بهت بم
I feel a little weird about being here.
من يزره حس عجيبي دارم از اينکه اينجام
- Why? Don't.
را؟ نداشته باش
- Well, I don't know if you know this,
خوب،نميدونم اينو ميدوني يا نه
but, uh, I'm a few years older than you.
ولي ،اه،من يه ند سالي از تو بزرترم
- You are?
جدي؟
- Just a few, yeah,
فقط يکم
and I'm not necessarily saying-
....و لزوما هم اينو نميم که
I don't want to get ahead of myself here.
من نميخوام بيشتر از حد خودم يش برم
Ifs just-
...يجواريي فقط
- Oh, Wail. 30"'!-
اوه،وايسا بينم،شرمنده
You-did you think this was, like, a romantic thing?
تو فکر کردي الان ما قضيمون رومانتک بازي ايناست؟
Just kidding.
شوخي کردم بابا
- Oh, my--
...اوه،خدا
- Come here.
بيا اينجا بينم
Try not to overthink things, okay?
سعي کن زياد فکر نکني،باشه؟
- You're talking to the wrong guy.
به يکي بو حاليش بشه
- Well, look
خوب،ببين
We connect really well, don! you think?
ما خيلي خوب با هم ارتباط برقرار ميکنيم تو اينطور فکر نميکني؟
- We do, yeah.
آره ميکنيم
I just can't figure out if ifs because you're advanced
من فقط نميتونم بفهمم که بخاطر اينه که تو نسبت به سنت بالا ميزني
or because I'm stunted,
يا من کويک
- It's because I'm advanced.
بخاطر اينه که من سن بالا ميزنم
. Maybe.
شايد
But I'm also a little stunted.
ولي منم يکم کويک ميزنم
- Look, I want lo like things slowly, okay?
ببين،من دلم ميخواد يزاي بينمون يواش يش بره،باشه؟
- Yeah, okay.
آره،باشه
Me too.
منم همينطور
- But I would like to kiss you
ولي باز من دلم ميخواد که ببوسمت
on your forehead.
از يشوني
Can I kiss you on your forehead?
ميتونم يشونيتو ببوسم؟
Say yes'
بو آره
- Yea.
آره
- And your chin'!
بعد ونتو
May I kiss your chin?
ميتونم ونتو ببوسم؟
- Sorry. Hi, sorry.
شرمنده
Just need to grab something.
فقط يه يزي وردارم برم
- Roommates.
هم اتاقيه
- Can we-are you hungry'!
ميشه؟...شنت نيست؟
- I could eat.
ميتونم بخورم
- Yeah?
آره؟
Maybe we could go into town and grab something?
شايد بريم سمت شهر و يه يزي بخوريم؟
- That'll take too long.
اونجوري خيلي طول ميکشه
I have class at 2:00.
من ساعت 2 کلاس دارم
- On.
اوه
good and even closer.
ولي،من يه جارو ميشناسم که هم خوبه هم نزديکتره
- Hey, Dean.
سلام،دين
- You get a job here?
اينجا کار ير آوردي؟
- I wish.
اي کاش
Hey, I seem to have lost my friend.
هي،انار دوستمو مش کردم
You mind if I...
...مشکلي نداري اه من
What are you working on?
داري رو ي کار ميکني؟
- Yeah, ifs this...
آره،اين يه
novel.
رمانه
- Good for you.
خوشبحالت
- I fill!!!
فکر کنم
- You happy with if?
خوشحالت ميکنه؟
- Not really.
نه واقعا
- Haw you been? Any batter?
طوريا بودي؟ بهتر شدي؟
- No.
نه
I kind of just wish this would all be over
يجورايي فقط آرزو ميکنم همه ي اين قضايا
as soon as possible.
هري سريعتر تموم شه
Why did you lave it here so much'!
را اينقدر اينجارو دوسش داري؟
- It's the only time you get to do this, you know?
اين تنها باريه که ميتوني اينکارو بکني ميدوني ؟
You get to sit around and read books all day,
ميتوني بشيني اينور اونر و کل روز واسه خودت کتاب بخوني
have really great conversations about idea;
بحث هاي خيلي خوب در مورد ايده ها انجام بدي
People out in the world, they're not really doing that.
آدما اون بيرون تو دنيا همين کارايي رو نميکنن
Think about it.
بهش فکر کن
You could go up to everyone here and say, 'I'm a poet,"
ميتوني اينجا يش هرکسي بري و بي من يه شاعرم
and no one will punch you in the face.
و بعد هيشکيم با مشت نخوابونه تو فکت
I mean, that's something.
اينم يه يزيه واسه خودش
- Yeah.
آره
I get that.
رفتم ي ميي
I just can't get around the fact
فقط نميتونم اين حقيقت باش کنار بيام
that I'm, like, aggressively unhappy here.
که من به شدت اينجا احساس ناراحتي ميکنم
- Jesse.
جسي
- That's my number, if you ever want to talk,
اين شماره ي منه محض اينه يه موقع خواستي حرف بزني
. HEY- . HO)'-
سلام
- Please tell me this is Vanessa's.
تورو خدا بهم بو اين ماله ونساست
- Nope, that's mine.
نخير،مال شخص اينجانبه
- Wait, you actually read this'?
وايسا بينم،تو واقعا اينو خوندي؟
- Yeah.
آره
- All of it?
همشو؟
- Unironically?
الکي نيا
- Very sincerely'
خيلي صادقانه
- What is it with you girls and vampires?
اين ه فازيه بين شما دخترا و خون آشاما؟
What's it about'?
درمورد ي هست؟
- Vampires.
خون آشاما
- No, what's it about?
نه،موضوعش يه؟
- I don't understand. Is it good?
درک نميکنم خوبم هست؟
- No.
نه
I mean, yeah. But no.
يعني،آره ولي نه
- Well, then why read it'?
س را ميخونيش؟
- 'Cause I like it.
بخاطر اينکه ازش خوشم مياد
- That's no reason to read something.
اينکه دليلي براي خوندن يزي نميشه
- Why else would you read something?
ديه واسه ي بايد يه يز بخوني مه؟
- Seriously.
جدي ميم
Many amazing books in the world.
کلي کتاب فوق العاده تو دنيا هست
Why would you read this?
تو را بايد اينو بخوني؟
- Okay, I hate this conversation.
اوکي،از اين بحث متنفرم
Can we stop?
ميشه بس کنيم؟
- Wait, this is a trilogy, right?
وايسا ببينم،اين سه انست آره؟
- I'm afraid to answer that.
ميترسم جوابتو بدم
- You've read three of these?
تو سه تاشم خوندي؟
- Have you ever read one of them?
تو تاحالا يدونه از اينارم خوندي؟
What do you think?
خودت ي فکر ميکني شمک؟
- How can you hate something if you've never read it?
طور ميتوني از يه يزي متنفر باشي وقتي حتي نخونديش
I mean, isn't that like what repressive regimes do?
منظورم اينه که،اين همون کاري نيست که رژيماي سرکوب ر انجام ميدن؟
You want to bum books you don't like?
ميخواي کتابايي که ازشون خوشت نمياد و آتيش بزني؟
- You're right. You know what l'm gonna do?
راست ميي ميدوني ميخوام يکار کنم؟
Rm gonna read thin book, all of it
ميخوام اين کتابو بخونم،همشو
And then we can discuss it.
و بعد ميتونيم درموردش بحث کنيم
- Right now? - Yeah, why not')
همين الان؟ آره را که نه
I mean, how long can it take, really?
يعني،مه جدي قراره قدر طول بکشه؟
This is great, a little book club.
خيليم عاليه،يه کتاب بازيه کوولو
- Seriously?
الان جدي ميي؟
- YUP-
آره
See ya soon.
زودي ميبينمت
Oh, no, this isn't what it-
....اوه نه،اين اونيزي نيست که به نظ
I'm reading it as a dare.
به ها حکم بهم دادن
It's a bet, actually.
يه شرطه،به خدا
I loved your class!
عاشق کلاست بودما
- Should I start'?
شروع کنم؟
- Please.
خواهش ميکنم
- OK!!-
اوکي
I liked it.
ازش خوشم اومد
It was fun and stupid. - Mm-hmm
سررم کننده و احمقانه بود هممم
- And it passed the time.
و يجورايي وقت ذرون
And it's not Tolstoy, but it's also not television.
درسته تولستويم نيست ولي حداقلش تلويزيونم نيست
And it made me happy.
تازه خوشحالمم کرد
Now you.
حالا تو
- Thank you. - Mm.
ممنونم اهمم
- This...
اين
is the worst book
بدترين کتابيه که
ever written
تابحال
in English.
به انليسي نوشته شده
- So there are worse books written in other languages?
س کتاباي بدتري تو زباناي ديم هست؟
- Probably not
احتمالا نه
unless this book is translated into other languages.
مر اينکه همين کتاب به زباناي ديم ترجمش کنن
- Okay, we really-
باشه،ما واقعا
we don't need to do this.
نيازي نداريم اينکارو بکنيما
- No, please, let's.
...نه،لطفا،بزار
I need to know haw you read these-
نياز دارم بدونم که طور اين
whew, l guess you call them sentences-
ميدونم واله،فکر کنم تو بهشون ميي جملرو خوندي
close the book, and feel anything
کتاب بستي و بعد حسي
other than offended and sad?
غير از دلخوري و غمينيم بهت دست داده
- Well, millions of people like it.
خوب،ميليون ها آدم ازش خوششون اومده
- So when millions of people like something,
س وقتي ميليون تا آدم از يه يزي خوششون بياد
that means it's good?
يعني اون يز خوبه؟
- No, it means millions of people like it
نه يعني ميليونا آدم خوششون اومده
These books make people happy.
اين کتاب باعث ميشه ملت خوشحال شن
We don't always have to be thinking about poli-sci
ما هميشه مجبور نيستيم که در مورد سياست و منطق بخونيم
or reading Chaucer, which, by the way, I hated.
يا اوسر که ازش متنفرم هستم
- You're not supposed to like it.
تو قرار نيست ازش خوشت بياد که
- But then why read if?
س را بخونمش؟
You love college so much, right?
تو خيلي دانشاه دوست داري درسته؟
Isn't it all about understanding different points of view'?
دانشاه همش درمورد درک کردن نقطه نظرات متفاوت نيست؟
- It's also about developing taste.
همنين درمورد بهتر کردن سليقتم هست
- That was snobby. You're a snob.
اين ديه افاده اي بود تو خيلي ر افاده اي
- No, I'm not
نه نيستم
- Yea, you are.
را هستي
You think it's cool to hale things.
تو فکر ميکني باحاله که بعضي يزارو بي نقص نشون بدي
And it's not. It's boring.
که نيست خسته کنندست
Talk about what you love,
صحبت کردن درمورد يزايي که دوست داري
and keep quiet about what you don't
و هي حرفي نزدن درمورد يزايي که نداري
- Look, I know how this sounds, but trust me.
ببين،ميدونم طوري به نظر ميرسه،ولي
This is a big deal, okay'?
اين قضيه ي خيلي مهميه؟باشه؟
This country is in bad shape,
اين کشور توي حالت بديه
and it has to do, in large part, I think,
و بيشترشم من فکر ميکنم که ربطي داره
with people liking things that are very, very bad.
يه همين يزاي مزخرف خيلي بد دوست دارن
- But according to you,
خب تو داري اينو ميي
Why are you the one who gets to decide what's good and bad?
را تو اون کسي هستي که ميتونه فرق بين خوب و بد تشخيص بده؟
And do you only want to surround yourself
و تو دلت ميخواد دور اطرافت ر کني از آدمايي
with people who've read the same books as you?
که همون کتابي رو که تو ميخوني ميخونن؟
- I guess we're gonna have to move on to a specific example-
فکر کنم بايد بريم سمت يه نمونه ي بارز
- Where are you?
کجايي تو؟
- What do you mean?
يعني ي؟
- I mean, you are somewhere,
يعني،يه جايي هستي
but it's not here.
ولي اينجا نيستي
- No, I'm-l'm here.
نه،من اين اينجام
- So why are we spending all our time
س را ما داريم کل وقتمون
having a stupid argument about a book?
صرف يه بحث مسخره در مورد يه کتاب ميکنيم؟
- Hey, Peter.
هي،يتر
- Zibby
زيبي
- Peter.
يتر
- What the hell are you doing here?
اينجا ه غلطي ميکني؟
I don't know'
نميدونم
- You know how old I am?
ميدوني من ند سالمه
- No, how old are you?
نه ند سالته؟
none of your goddamn business.
به تو هي ربطي نداره
Do you know how old I feel like I am?
ميدوني احساس ندساله هارو دارم؟
Since I was 19, I have never felt not 19.
از زمان 19 ساليم ديه هيوقت غير از 19 ساله خودمو حس نميکردم
But I shave my face, and I look in the mirror,
ولي صورتمو ميزنم و به آينه ناه ميکنم و
and I'm forced to say,
مجبورم که بم
"This is not a 19-year-old staring back at me, “
اين يه سر 19 ساله نيست که داره  بهم ناه ميکنه
Teaching here all these years,
همه ي اين سالها تو درس دادن
I've had to be very clear with myself
بايد با خودم خيلي روراست ميبودم
that even though I'm surrounded by 19-year-old:
که ره تمام اطرافمو 19 ساله ها رفتن
and I may have felt 19,
و ممکنه منم احساس 19 سالي کنم
I'm not 19 anymore.
ولي نيستم
You follow me?
مييري ي ميم؟
- Yeah.
آره
- Nobody feels like an adult.
هيشکي بالغ نيست
It's the world's dirty secret.
اين راز کثيف دنياست
- How perfect is the universe?
ه جاي خوبيه اين عالم
- You're still here?
تو هنوز اينجايي؟
- Lucky for you,
شانس توِ
'cause you look like you could use a friend.
ون قيافت شبيه اوناست که به يه دوست احتياج دارن
Did you know there's so many preservatives in the food we eat
ميدونستي کلي نهدارنده توي غذاهايي که ما ميخوريم هست
that they're finding it's taking longer
که تازه فهميدن باعث ميشه
for our bodies to decompose once we die?
متلاشي شدن بدنمون وقتي مرديم ديرتر انجام بشه؟
- No way. Really?
نه بابا؟ جدي؟
- Preservatives, man. messed up.
نهدارنده ها رفيق افتضاحن
Want some good news?
يکم خبر خوب ميخواي؟
- Please.
جون مادرت
- Caterpillars- give me my hat.
کرم ابريشما کلاهمو بم بده
They're just scouting along, right,
همش اينور و اينور جستجو ميکنن درسته؟
being caterpillars.
کرمک بازي ميکنن ديه
At some point, these cells show up called imaginal cells.
بعد يه زماني،سر و کله ي يه سلولايي يدا ميشه که بهشون مين سلولاي تخيلي
Scientists don't know where they come from
دانشمندا نميدونم اونا از کجا يداشون ميشه
or why they appear,
يا اينکه را يداشون ميشه
but these imaginal cells show up inside the caterpillar
ولي اين سلولاي تخيلي سر و کلشون توي بدن کرم ابريشم يدا ميشه
and say, 'Get psyched, caterpillar!
و بهش مين،عشق و حال کن کرم بريشم
It's butterfly-turning-into time."
وقته تبديل شدن به روانست
- Mm-hmm.
ممم
- And whit do all the other caterpillar calla do
و بقيه ي سلولاي کرم ابريشم ي مين وقتي
when these imaginal cells show up?
اين سلولاي تخيلي سرو کلشون يدا ميشه؟
- I have no idea.
هي ايده اي ندارم
- They attack 'em!
بهشون حمله ميکنن
Try to kill 'em!
سعي ميکنن بکشنشون
They're like, 'Screw you, imaginal cells.
مين،ه خوردين سلولاي تخيلي
'We're happy being a caterpillar.
ما از اينکه کرم بريشميم خوشحاليم
Gel lost!“
برين مشين
Bu! eventually, the imaginal cells keep growling
ولي بالاخره سلولاي تخيلي به رشدشون ادامه ميدن
and overtake the destiny of the caterpillar
و سرنوشت کرم ابريشم دستشون مييرن
and will it into this cocoon.
و ميفرستنش تو يله
And then guess what happens next.
و بعد حدس بزن ي ميشه
into a butterfly.
ميشه روانه
- The caterpillar turns into a butterfly.
کرم ابريشم ميشه روانه
- That's awesome.
خدا بود
- I know it is!
ميدونم
- Yeah, that's good.
آره،خوب بود
- And that is why there is no reason to be afraid,
و بخاطر همينه که هي دليلي نداره که ترس داشته باشي
because everything is okay.
بخاطر اينکه همه يز خوبه
- Yeah, I don't know if I believe that.
آره،نميدونم ميتونم باورش کنم يا نه
- It has to be true.
بايد واقعيت داشته باشه
There can be no other way.
هي راه ديه اي وجود نداره
- You know, I'm not even sure if you're real.
ميدوني،من حتي مطمئن نيستم که تو واقعي يا نه
I mean, seriously.
جدي ميم
- Ifs all true, brother.
همه ي درسته داداش من
Whatever you believe.
هريُ دوست داري باور کن
- What is that?
اون يه؟
What are you drinking?
داري ي ميخوري؟
- H to the 2 to the O.
ا بره يش اُ بره يش 2
You should have some.
يکم بخور
Got to stay hydrated.
آدم بايد هيدراته بمونه (جسم مرکب با آب ميشه هيدراته همون آب بدن يا خري)
- All right.
خيلي خوب
Oh, thanks.
اوه،مرسي
Ooh!
اوه
You with me, bro?
با مني ديه داداش؟
Yeah.
آره
I like you, Nat'
ازت خوشم مياد،نت
Thanks for being my friend.
مرسي که دوستمي
- Easiest thing in the world.
راحت ترين کار توي دنياست
- I enjoyed this.
ازش لذت بردم
I'm off.
ما رفتيم
- You go get her, man.
برو بدستش بيار مرد
- Huh
هاه
Okay-
باشه
- Be love, man.
عشق باش مرد
Be love!
عشق باش
You seem happy.
به نظر خوشحال ميرسي
- I am.
هستم
- What happened?
ي شده مه؟
- I don't know.
نميدونم
Something.
يه ي
- Can I tell you some things?
ميتونم يه يزي بت بم؟
- Yeah, yeah, sure.
آره،آره حتما
- Okay, well, except for the book thing,
اوکي،غير از قضيه ي کتاب
which was genuinely super annoying,
که خيلي رو مخ بود
I-I feel really good about you.
من واقعا حس خوبي نسبت به تو دارم
It's been a while since I fell that way about someone.
خيلي ميذره از وقتي که يه همين حسي واسه کسي داشتم
And I like it.
و ازين خوشم مياد
- Yeah, me too.
آره،منم
- I want you lo slay here with me tonight
ازت ميخوام امشب يشم بموني
- You have a roommate,
تو که هم اتاقي داري
- She's sleeping elsewhere.
يه جاي ديه ميخوابه
- Ah.
آه
- So will you stay here?
ي ميموني اينجا؟
- Yea.
آره
- Good.
خوبه
But I have in tell you something.
ولي بايد يه يزيو بهت بم
Um...
..اوم
this-it would be my, um...
...اين ميشه
first time.
اولين بارم
But I want to.
ولي خودم ميخواما
With you.
با تو
- Okay, um...
اوکي،اوم
I have to-
...من بايد
hold on.
صبر کن
I'll-l'll be back in a second, okay'?
يه ثانيه ديه برميردم باشه؟
- OK!!-
باشه
- I should never have told you that
هيوقت نبايد اونو بهت ميفتم
good.
خوبه
I'm-l'm glad you did.
خوشحالم که فتي
- So is that a problem?
س الان موشکل داريم؟
- Well, yeah, it is.
موشکل؟ آره داريم
- WM?
را
Okay, well, first of all, I'm 35.
اوکي،اولا اينکه من 35 سالمه
- You don'! look it - Thank you.
ولي اينطور که به نظر نميرسي مرسي
- Plus, it doesn't bother me.
به اضافه ي اينکه،اصلا اذيتم نميکنه اين قضيه
- Well, it bothers me.
خوب منو که ميکنه
- Well, it shouldn't.
خوب نبايد بکنه
Age is a stupid thing to obsess over.
سن خيلي يز احمقانه ايه که بخواي باش به خودت يربدي
What if reincarnation is real, huh?
ي ميشه اه تولد دوباره حقيقت داشته باشه؟
Think about that.
فکر کن بهش
What if I'm, like, thousands of years older than you?
ي اه من هزاران سال سنمه الان؟
- Okay, that's not really a sound argument.
اوکي،اين اصلا يه بحث عاقلانه به نظر نميرسه
- Why not')
را نه
- Because ifs like saying,
بخاطر اينکه مثل اين ميمونه بي
'What if reality is all an illusion?"
ي اه حقيقت همش توهمه؟
Then there are no consequences to anything.
بعد ديه هي يزي هي عواقبي نداره
We're completely off the hook,
و مام کلا بدرد لاي جرز ميخوريم
And I believe in consequences.
و منم از اوناشم که به عواقب عقيده دارم
- No, you believe in guilt.
نه،تو به ناه عقيده داري
- Maybe.
شايد
But guilt before we act is called morality.
ولي ناه قبل از عمل اسمش اخلاقه
Why did you come back here?
اصلا را برشتي اينجا
- To see you, but I didn't know that you-
که تورو ببينم ولي من نميدونستم که تو
- Why should that matter'!
اصلا اون را بايد مهم باشه
I mean, inn'! it, I don't know, flattering?
منظورم اينه که اصلا همين يزي تعريف کردن از تو حساب نميشه؟
- Listen.
وش کن
Elizabeth.
اليزابت
Sex is really complicated, okay?
سکس خيلي ييدست باشه؟
I didn't quite understand that when I was younger,
من زياد نميفهميدم يعني ي وقتي جوونتر بودم
but I do now.
ولي الان ميفهمم
- Okay, look, I didn't sign one of those contracts
اوکي،ببين من از اون قراردادا که حتما بايد بدي
when I was in high school, okay?
وقتي توي دبيرستان بودم امضا نکردم خوب؟
I'm not a prude or whatever.
کوته فکر و از اين حرفام نيستم
just, I never met anyone that I trusted
فقط،هيوقت آدمي رو که بتونم بهش اعتماد کنم
or even liked enough
يا حتي به اندازه ي کافي ازش خوشم بياد يدا نکردم
until now.
تا الان
- I can't.
من نميتونم
- Are you not attracted to me?
تو اصلا منو جذاب ميدوني؟
- Na. I mean, yea, I am.
نه يعني،آره ميدونم
It's just.
فقط اينکه
I also care about you a lat already, somehow.
يجورايي همينجوريش کلي بهت اهميت ميدم
- So, um, essentially,
س،اوم،اساسا
you don't want to sleep with me
تو نميخواي با من بخوابي
because you like and respect me too much.
بخاطر اينکه تو خيلي منو دوست داري و بهم احترام ميزاري؟
- Basically.
اساسا
Yeah.
آره
- That's, like, the saddest thing over.
اين غم انيزترين يزي بود که شنيدم
- Look, I want to be in your life.
ببين،من ميخوام که توي زندي تو باشم
I do.
جدي ميخوام
- Yeah, I already have an older brother, okay'?
باشه،من همين الان يه برادر بزرتر از خودم دارم باشه؟
And I don't need some mentor.
به يه معلم سرخونم احتياجي ندارم
- I can'! just say yes to everything.
من که نميتونم به همه يز بله بم
Elizabeth.
اليزابت
- Slop calling me that.
ديه اونجوري صدام نکن
- What?
ي
- No one calls me that
هيشکي منو اينجوري صدا نميکنه
You need to leave right now.
تو همين الان بايد بري
I'm really upset, and you need to go.
من واقعا نارااحتم و توام بايد بري
- OK!!-
باشه
- Get out!
برو بيرون
- Well, well, well.
خوب،خوب،خوب
- Now I remember you.
حالا تورو يادم مياد
- You do?
مياد؟
- Not really.
نه واقعا
- Rough day?
روز سختي بوده؟
- Yeah.
آره
- "Mock on. Mock on.
تمسخر کن
"'Tis all in vain.
که همه يز غيرممکن
"You throw the sand against the wind,
تو شن را بر باد زني
and the wind blows it back again."
و باد برتو شن ( هرونه استفاده از ترجمه ي اين شعري که فته شده با اسم صاحب علي خاشعي مجازه جون مادرتون با فرهن باشين مرد باشين)
- Blake.
بليک
. A-plus.
20 شدي
- French fries.
سيب زميني سرخ کرده
I wan jun about in order a basket.
تازه داشتم يه بستشو سفارش ميدادم
. HO)'-
باشه
Can you get me a beer'?
برام يه آبجو مييري؟
- Yeah, have mine.
آره،مال منو بخور
- Of course, I'm thrilled.
کاملا، خيلي هيجان زده شده بودم
Newly minted PhD.
ي ا ديه تازه ضرب خورده
I'm feeling very fancy
احساس خيلي خوبي دارم
and officially teaching Ode on a Grecian Um
و ديه رسما دارم غزل و قصيدرو توي يونان جديد درس ميدم
for the first time.
براي اولين بار
It's like heaven, right?
مثل بهشت ميمونه درسته؟
- - Right. Right. right. right.
آره آره آره
- And I decide to be a little dramatic.
بعد تصميم رفتم که يکم هيجانيش کنم
I'm really gonna go for it
ميخواستم برم تو قضيه و
and just recite the whole thing out loud.
همه يز از حفظ بلند بلند بخونم
What the hell, right'?
هري شد شد ديه آره؟
- Sure.
حتما
- And it's going very well, if I do say so myself.
و اه بخواي از دهن من بشنوي خيليم خوب يش رفت
And as I reach the immortal final lines
همونجوري که به آخرين خطهاي جاودان شده ي
of one of the great poems ever written in English,
يکي از بهترين شعر هايي که تابحال به انليسي نوشته شده
I hear myself say the following:
:صداي خودمو ميشنوم که دارم ميم
"Beauth is trudy, trudy beauth."
زيبايي حق است و حق زيبا (به فته ي خود کارردان يکم بازي با کلمات کرده که مثلا زن جو يونان قديم رفته بودتش)
- "That is all ye know on Earth and all ye need know."
اين تنها يزيست در اين دنيا ميخواهي بداني و نياز داري که بداني
- That is great
عالي بود
Great story.
داستان خيلي خوبي بود
When did you fall for the Romantics?
کي عاشق ادبيات رمانتيک شدي؟
Was it, like- I'm just curious,
...اونموقع ها بود که يکم کنجکاوم
but was it in college or grad school?
دانشاه بود يه دکترات بود
'Cause I knew almost nothing about those guys
ونکه من تقريبا هيي درمورد اون آدما
before your class.
قبل از کلاس تو نميدونستم
Your class.
کلاست
Och, I can gush, right'?
ميتونم آه بکشم که،آره؟
I mean, I still think about it.
منظورم اينه که،من هنوزم بهش فکر ميکنم
Ifs just-
فقط اينکه
What?
ي؟
- You're very enthusiastic.
تو خيلي مشتاق ميزني
- I guess.
فکر کنم
- I have a car.
من يه ماشين دارم
- ORGY-
به سلامتي
- I would like for you to get in it with me,
دوست دارم که توام با من توش سوار شي
and I would like to drive us somewhere.
و دوست دارم مارو يه جايي ببري
- Where?
کجا؟
- Don't worry about the fries,
نران سيب زمينيا نباش
They know me here.
منو اينجا ميشناسنم
- Oh, hey, man.
نوکرتم دادا
Okay, you got to go.
اوکي ديه باس بري
- What?
نَمَنه؟
- Out. Go, now.
بيرون، بي،الان
- Owl Are you serious?
او،جدي ميي؟
- YUP-
آره
- Yeah, I don't have to, uh, stay the night or anything,
آره خوب،همين نيازي نيست،اوه، شبو اينجا بمونم يا يه ي تو اين مايه ها
but could I-could I at least catch my breath?
ولي حداقل يه نفس که ميتونم تازه کنم خبر مرم؟
- Sure.
حتما
How long do you think that'll be?
فکر ميکني قدر طول بکشه؟
- What? - No, no.
يه؟ هيي هيي
It's just funny to me all of a sudden.
فقط همه ي برام يهمو بامزه شد
- What about it is amusing to you'?
يه اين قضيه برات جالبه؟
- Your post-coital cigarette, for one, is amusing to me.
يکيش سيار بعد از سکست برام جالبه
- What, you never smoked?
يه،تو هيوقت سيار نکشيدي؟
- No, I did. - But you quit
را کشيدم ولي ترک کردي
- Yeah. - Pussy.
آره ترسو
- Okay, you are the same Judith Fairfield
اوکي،تو همون جوديث فيرفيلدي
I took British Romantic literature from?
من باش کلاس ادبيات رومانتيک داشتم؟
- "From whom I took British Romantic literature,"
هستي که من باش کلاس ادبيات رومانتيک داشتم
and yes, that's me.
و بله،خودمم
But just because we screwed, don't assume we're suddenly-
ولي فقط بخاطر اينکه ما با همديه سکس کرديم فکر نکن که يهويي
what is it you kids say nowadays?
ي بهش ميين شما به هاي امروزي؟
BFFs?
رفيق جون جوني؟
- Yeah, that's not really-
...آره،اين واقعا اونجوري که من
- I mean, what do we really know about each other?
منظورم اينه که،ما واقعا درمورد همديه ي ميدونيم؟
You're a nonsmoker. Congratulations.
تو يه کسي هستي که سيار نميکشه تبريک ميم
You're going to live to be a hundred.
تو يدونه از اوناشي که تا صد سالي عمر ميکنن
But what does it matter if your life is joyless?
ولي خوب که ي اينکار اه زنديت بخواد بدون لذت باشه
And it will be. Trust me.
که خواهد شد بهم اعتماد کن
- What's happening here?
الان داره ه اتفاقي مي افته؟
- You're gelling your clothes and you're leaving,
داري لباساتو ميوشي و مييي به بازي
and I'm going to take an Ambien.
و منم يه آمبين ميخورم (داروي خواب آور)
- No, I meant, what is hap-
نه،منظورم اين بود که
- I mean, seriously.
يعني،جدي ميما
You weren't thinking we were gonna cuddle
فکر نکردي که کل شب قراره همديرو بغل کنيم و
the rest of the night as I read you Wordsworth?
منم برات از کتبا وردزورت بخونم؟
- Not anymore.
ديه نه
- Good.
خوبه
I've taught at this school for over 20 years.
من 20 ساله که دارم توي اين دانشاه درس ميدم
I've seen the emergence of your kind like an infection-
و رفتن امثال شمارم زياد ديدم مثل يه بيماري وايردار ميمونه
all these effete, overarticulate man-boys
يه مشت به خونيه از کار افتاده ي زِر زِرو
who never learned to toughen up.
که هيوقت ياد نرفتن که مرد باشن
Don't be one of them,
تو يکي از اونا نباش
Go work with your hands.
برو يکم از اين دستا کار بکش
Build something.
يه يزي بساز
Punch someone in the face.
با مشت بخوابون تو صورت يکي
- WWI.
واي
Too bad Norman Mailer's dead.
خيلي بد شد که نورمن ميلر ند اخلاق مرد
would have been perfect for each other.
شما دوتا واسه همديه ساخته شدين اصلا
- Shall I count to ten?
باس تا 10 بشمرم؟
- Wail, just, can-
وايسه،فقط،
hold on just one second, okay?
يه يه ثانيه صبر کن باشه؟
You don't seem very happy.
تو به نظر خوشحال نمياي
Your powers of deduction are stunning.
قدرت استنتجايت يدونه باشه
You must have gone to a very good college.
بايد يه دانشاه خوب رفته باشي
- I'm just confused how-
من يکم موندم
I mean, you're a tenured professor
منظورم اينه که،تو يه روفسور رسمي
in one of the most prestigious English departments
تو يکي از معتبرترين دارتمان هاي ادبيات انليسي
in the country.
کشوري
That's not fulfilling?
اين اصلا برات کافي نيست؟
- Sit through a faculty meeting at a liberal arts college,
يه بار بشين توي ردهمايي استاداي دانشاه هنرهاي زيبا
Mr. Young Person.
آقا جوونه
I assure you, you will lose all faith in humanity.
بعد بهت اطمينان ميدم که کل ايمانت به انسانيت از دست ميدي س اه اينطوره
- Okay, but what about the classroom?
اوکي،س کلاس در ي ميشه؟
There had lo have been some joy there
بايد يه لذتي اونجا باشه ديه
I mean, you were such a good teacher.
منظورم اينه که،تو استاد خوبي بودي که س
- Thank you.
مرسي
I like to teach.
من درس دادن دوست دارم
I used to love it.
قبلنام عاشقش بودم
- What happened?
ي اتفاقي افتاد؟
- Life happened.
زندي اتفاق افتاد
- Okay, I'm gonna need a little bit more'
اوکي،من به يکم بيشتر از اين جمله نياز دارم
- Well, that's all you're gonna get.
خوب،اين همه يزي بود که يرت اومد
Unlike you, I'm not from the 'let me tell you
بر عکس تو،من از نسل اون آدماي بزار
every sick, sordid detail of my life" generation.
جزئيات مزخرف و کثافت زنديمزنديم برات باشم بيرون نيتسم
I value discretion.
من براي احتياط ارزش قائلم
I loathe self-pity.
و از ترحم به خودم بيزارم
So let's just leave it at this:
س بزار قضيرو با اين تموم کنيم
people are disappointing.
آدما نا اميد کنندن
- Yeah, it's just, I would think-
آره،فقط اينکه من فکر ميکردم
- Don't get comfortable. - Sorry.
راحت نشو مينيم بابا شرمنده
I would just think
من فکر ميکردم
that spending so much time with those poems
که کلي وقت ذروندن با اون شعرها
would make you more, you know, optimistic and hopeful.
باعث ميشه تو ،ميدوني خوشبين و اميدوار بشي
- Nonsense.
مزخرفه
They were miserable men
اون نويسنده ها يه مشت آدم بدبخت بودن
who were granted a few moments of transcendence,
که بخاطر ند لحظه بهشون يه برتري داده شده
and they had the talent and foresight
و اونام اين ديد و بصيرت رو داشتن که
to grab pen and paper and write it down.
کاغذ و قلم بيرن دستشونُ اونُ بنويسن
Byron was probably the happiest of the lot,
بايرون احتمالا خوشحالترينشون بوده که
only because he put his dick in everything.
اونم فقط بخاطر اين بود که کيرش تو همه ي ميکرد
- This is the saddest evening of my life
اين غم انيزترين شب زنديمه
- Get used to it.
بهش عادت کن
My advice to you is this:
يه نصيحت ميکنم بهت
put some armor around that gooey little heart of yours.
يه زره دور اون قلب سبندت بکش
- Well, at least I appreciate the irony.
خوب حداقل از اين طنز طعنه آميزم خوشم اومد
I just had the least romantic night of my life
که بي رمانتيک ترين شب زنديم
with a Romantics professor.
با يه رفسور ادبيات رمانتيک ذروندم
For what it's worth,
بخاطر اينکه ارزشش داره بم
I meant everything I said about your class.
هري که درمورد کلاست فتم از ته دل بود
It opened something in me,
يه يزيرو توي قلبم باز کرد
and I'm grateful for it.
که براش شکرزارم
And if my heart is gooey,
و اه قلبم سبندست
you're at least partially responsible for that.
حداقل تو يکم نسبت بهش مسئولي
- So you're still uninspired by admissions.
س هنوزم با ذيرشايي که ميکني حال نميکني
- Yeah, pretty much.
آره،زياد
- No little Jesse Fishers out there?
هي جسي فيشر کوولويي اون بيرون نيست؟
- Well, if there are, I'm not meeting them,
خوب،ارم هست،من که نميبينمشون
- Well, maybe you're just not recognizing them.
خوب،شايد فقط تشخيصشون نميدي
Anyway,
به هرحال
I do appreciate you coming by.
من حال کردم که تو اومدي يه سري زدي
I really do.
واقعا کردم
It's great to see you one last time
خيلي خوب بود که يه بار براي آخرين بارم ببينمت
before I get the hell out of here.
قبل از اينکه از اينجا مشم بيرون
- You feeling any better about things?
حالت بهتر شده در مورد همه ي؟
- Well,
خوب
I tried to turn the clock back.
سعي کردم که ساعتمو برشردونم
it doesn't work.
ولي اينجوري کار نميکنه
- No, it doesn't.
نه،نميکنه
- Now I just-
حالا فقط
I keep waiting to feel more resolve somehow.
بايد منتظر بشينم که يه تصميمي بيرم
What if I'm like one of those prisoners
ي ميشه اه من مثل اون زنداني باشم
that gets paroled
که عفو مشروط بهش ميخوره
and finds he can't handle life on the outside
و ميفهمه ديه نميتونه از س زندي اون بيرون بربياد
so he commits a petty crime
س دوباره يه جرم کويک مرتکب ميشه
so he can go back to what he knows?
که بررده به جايي که ميشناستش
- You think this place is a prison?
فکر ميکنه اينجا زندانه؟
- Well, any place you don't leave is a prison.
خوب،هرجايي که نتوني ترک کني زندانه
Well, whatever.
خوب،حالا هري
OKAY- - OK!!-
باشه
Hey.
هي
You know why you're my second favorite professor of all time?
ميدوني را تو دومين بهتيرن استادي هستي که داشتم؟
- I have no idea.
هي ايده اي ندارم
by authors you hated.
ون تو مارو مجبور ميکردي کتابايي رو بخونيم که از نويسنده هاش متنفر بودي
Feel good about what you did here.
در مورد کاري که اينجا کردي احساس خوبي داشته باش
- Thank you.
مرسي
Gel in your car now, and leave me be.
سوار ماشينت باش و بزار به حال خودم باشم
- "Dear Zibby, oven alter all these months,
زيبي عزيز،حتي بعد از اين همه مدت
"I'm still half-expecting a letter from you
من هنوز يه نصفه انتظار اينو دارم که يه نامه از تو
"to be sitting in my mailbox.
توي صندوق نامم بشينه
"I'm sure you have little left to say to me at this point,
مطمئنم يه يزايي مونده که ميخواي الان بهم بي
'bu! your letters are very much missed.
ولي نامه هات همنان نايداست
"I know I hurt you, and I'm sorry.
ميدونم که بهت صدمه زدم و خيلي متاسفم
“Any bone-headed moves I made
هر کار سر سري که انجام دادم
'were born of confusion and not malice.
زاده ي ريشاني بود نه کينه توزي
"That said, I've been feeling lately the stirring:
فته ميشه که من اين اواخر يه حس هيحان انيزي دارم
"of something I can only call growth
از يزي که ميتونم اسمش بزارم يشرفت
"It's a tribute of sorts to say that someone 16 years my junior
به نوعي مايه ي احترامه که بم شخصي 16 سال کوکتر از من
'helped me finally start acting my age.
بهم کمک کرد که به اقتضاي سنم عمل کنم
"A wise man in a red hat once told me,
زاهدي توي کلاهِ قرمزي يک بار بهم فت
“Everything is okay.'
که همه يز خوبه
"I didn't believe him then,
اون زمان باورش نکردم
but for some reason, I'm starting to.'
ولي به دلايلي دارم ميکنم
- Sorry, we're closed!
شرمنده،ما بسته ايم
Oh,
اوه
Hey.
سلام
- Are you here for this?
بخاطر اين اومدين اينجا؟
I always notice you reading it when you're in here.
هميشه ميديدم وقتي مياين اينجا اينو ميخونينش
- Yeah.
آره
Any bookstore I'm in, I have to read then.
هرکتاب فروشي که ميرم بايد سه صفحه ي آخر کتاب بخونم
Last three pages.
سه صفحه ي آخر
- I know. They're devastating.
ميدونم ويرانرن اصلا
- Yeah.
آره
I'm Jesse.
من جسيم
- I'm Ana.
من آنام
- Hi.
سلام
I love books.
من عاشق کتابام
I do in, like, the dorkiest way possible.
واقعا..به احمقانه ترين حالت ممکن
- Oh, me too.
اوه،منم همينطور
It's a problem.
خودش يه مشکليه
- Like, I love trees cause they give us books.
مثلا،من عاشق درختام بخاطر اينکه بهمون کتابارو ميدن
super cool of the trees to do that, light'!
دم درختا رم،نه؟
- I'm actually-
من در واقعا
this is weird.
يکم عجيبه
I'm actually trying to read less.
در واقع دارم سعي ميکنم يکم کمتر بخونم
- WM?
را؟
- I felt like I wasn't watching enough television.
احساس کردم به اندازه ي کافي تلويزيون ناه نميکنم
- No, l just-I started to feel like reading about life
نه،فقط احساس کردم که انار خوندن درمورد زندي
was taking time away from actually living life,
جاي واقعا زندي کردنمو رفته بود
so I'm trying to, like, accept invitations to things,
س دارم سعي ميکنم که يجورايي دعوتاي ملت قبول کنم
say "hi" to the world a little more.
و يکم بيشتر به دنيا بم سلام
- That sounds scary.
به نظر ترسناکه
It's going well?
خوب يش ميره؟
- It's..okay.
خو...به
Most of the time when I'm out,
بيشتر وقتا وقتي بيرونم
I keep thinking I'd be so much happier
همش فکر ميکنم که خيلي خوشحالتر بودم
in bed with a book,
اه تو تخت با يه کتاب بودم
and that makes me feel not super cool.
و اونموقع بهم اين حس خيلي خوبو نميده
I still read tons.
هنوزم خيلي خيلي ميخونما
I just feel like I'm more aware of a book's limitations.
فقط  احساس ميکنم بيشتر درمورد محدوديت کتباخوني اطلاع يدا کردم
Does that make sense?
اصلا با عقل جور دراومد حرفم؟
- Yeah, totally.
آره،کاملا
- How am I doing here?
دارم طور يش ميرم الان؟
- What? Here in this conversation?
ي؟ توي اين بحث؟
- Yeah.
آره
- Very well. You are doing great
خيلي خوب يکه يکه
So you maybe want to gel away from these books
س شايد دوست داشته باشي يکم از اين کتابا بکشي بيرون
and walk somewhere?
و يه جا قدمي بزني؟
- Yeah, okay.
آره،باشه
- Really? do it
واقعا؟ حتما،دوشواري نداره که
- Great. Great.
عاليه عايله
And feel free to invite your husband or boyfriend.
و اه خواستي دوست سر يا شوهرتم دعوت کني راحت باشا
- They're both pretty busy right now, so...
...هردوتاشون يجورايي سرشون شلوغه،س
- Probably just be us, then.
احتمالا فقط خودمونيم س
- Yeah. Just us.
آره فقط ما
- Hello.
سلام
- Oh, hi.
اوه،سلام
It's Dean
دينم
Franzen? We like the same writer.
فرنزن؟ همون نويسنده که هردوتامون دوسش داريم؟
- Right, hey. up?
درسته،سلام دين،ه خبر؟
- Uh, you gave me your number, and you told me to call you.
اوه،تو شمارتو بهم دادي و فتي که بهت زن بزنم
- Uh, yeah. No, ifs good to hear from you.
اوه،آره خوبه که صداتو ميشنوم
How are you doing?
جوريايي؟
- Uh, I'm pretty good, yeah.
اوه،خيلي خوب،آره
Things, um-
يزا،امم
I've been-
...من
- Dean?
دين؟
- I just took a bunch of pills.
همين الان يه مشت قرص خوردم
- What?
ي؟
- I just took a lot of pills.
همين الانا يه مشت قرص خوردم
- How many'?
ندتا؟
- I don't know. Um...
نميدونم ...اوم
I'm really scared.
واقعا خيلي ميترسم
- Where are you'! - In my dorm.
کجايي؟ توي خواباهم
- Stay-stay there, okay?
همونجا،همونجا بمون،باشه؟
Stay right there.
همونجا بمونيا
Okay, yeah, just stay ri- I'm gonna make a call,
باشه،آره،فقط همونجا بمون من يه زن ميزنم
and I'm gonna call-
و بعد بهت زن ميزنم
I need you lo stay by the phone, though, okay?
فقط ازت ميخوام شت تلفن بموني باشه؟
Dean?
دين؟
- Hey-
هي
- Hey, man.
هي،مرد
How you feeling?
طوري؟
- Kind of ridiculous.
يجورايي خنده دار
You didn't have to drive all the way out here.
لازم نبود رانندي کني بياي اينجاها
- I flaw, you bastard.
رواز کردم،حروم لقمه
- Thanks'
مرسي
For picking up the phone.
که تلفن برداشتي
I didn't know who else to call.
نميدونستم ديه به کي زن بزنم
- Can I make a suggestion?
ميتونم يه يشنهادي بکنم؟
- Yeah.
آره
- Stop reading this.
ديه اينو نخون
- WM?
را؟
- Because he killed himself, and you're not gonna do that.
بخاطر اينکه اين خودکشي کرد و تو قرار نيست اين کارو بکني
You need to read something else.
تو نيزا داري که يه يز ديه بخوني
Listen, don'! be a genius who dies young.
وش کن،يه نبغه نباش که جوون ميميره
Be one who dies old.
از اوناش باش که ير ميميره
Being old is cool.
ير بودن باحاله
Grow old and die old.
ير شو و ير بمير
It's a better arc.
يه روش بهتريه
Listen to me, man.
وش کن ببين ي ميم،مرد
This right now, all this stuff you're feeling,
اين اتفاقي که الان افتاده،همه ي اين يزايي که داري احساسشون ميکني
this is a footnote, okay'?
..همش ريز نوشته هاي ته صفحس
You're gonna graduate,
تو قراره فارغ التحصيل بشي
and you're gonna get out in the world
و قراره بري اون بيرون توي دنيا
and stumble into something like contentment.
و تو يه يه يزي به اسم قناعت قوطه بخوري
I know it.
ميدونم
- In that how ifs been for you?
اين همون اتفاقيه که واسه تو افتاده؟
- Hell, no.
اصلا نه
But some days are all right, you know?
ولي بعضي روزا که خوبه که ،درسته؟
Some days are like a gift,
بعضي روزا مثل يه هديه ميمونه
and some days suck.
و بعضي روزام افتضاحه
But all of that's okay.
و همش باهم خوبه
So I'm taking you off post-modernists.
س من تورو از اين کتاباي ست مدرن معاف ميکنم
What are you prescribing?
نسختون يه قربان؟
- There are these vampire books.
يه کتاباي خون آشامي هست
The kids love 'em.
به ها عاشقشن
Trust me, they will empty your mind completely.
بهم اطمينان کن،جون داداش کامل مخت از همه ي خالي ميکنه
- Why are you being so nice to me?
را اينقدر با من خوبي؟
You flew all the way beck here to see me,
اين همه راهو رواز کردي که منو ببيني
and we had, like, two conversations.
در صورتي که ما همش دوبار با هم حرف زديم
- I have a soft spot for good readers.
من براي کتاب خوناي خوب روحيه ي لطيفي دارم
They're hard to find these days'
يدا کردنشون امروز روز سخته
- I really did miss you.
من واقعا دلم برات تن شده بودا
You know, we had this thing happening,
ميدوني،يه يزي رو بينمون داشتيم
and it was so exciting, and then you were just gone.
و خيليم هيجان انيز بود و بعد تو ديه يهويي نبودي
But it's okay now.
ولي الان ديه همه ي اوکيه
I get it.
ميفهمم
I sometimes feel like I'm looking down on myself,
بعضي موقع ها حس ميکنم که انار دارم به اينکه ي هستم ناه ميکنم
this older, wiser mu
بعد انار يه نسخه ي بزرتر و داناتر من
watching over this 19-year-old rough draft
داره اين دختر 19 ساله ي اک نويس نشده رو مياد
who's full of all this potential
کسي که ر از تانسيلِ
but has to live more
ولي بايد بيشتر زندي کنه
to catch up with that other self somehow.
تا به اون يکي بزرتره برسه
And...
...و
I know I'll get there.
ميدونم که به اونجا ميرسم
It's just sometimes I think
فقط بعضي اوقات فکر ميکنم
I want to rush the process, you know?
دلم ميخواد يه کاري کنم خيلي سريع تر اتفاق بيفته
And I don't know.
و نميدونم
Maybe-maybe I thought you were some sort of shortcut.
شايد،شايد فکر کردم تو يه جور ميانبري برام
Does that make any sense?
حرفام با عقل جور در مياد؟
- If I wrote you, I would be like
اه برات مينوشتم هميشه اينجوري بودم که ميفتم
"This is the but rough draft ever.'
اين بهترين رک نويسه دنياست
- Seriously?
جدي ميي؟
- Roommates.
هم اتاقيه
- Well, I should gel back lo adulthood.
خيلي خوب ديه،وقتشه برردم به زندي آدم بزرا
- Yeah.
آره
See you there soon, I guess.
فکر کنم زود اونجا ميبينمت
. Bye, Zibby.
خدافظ زيبي
- Bye, Jesse
خدافظ جسي
- You're so beautiful and fascinating
توي خيلي خوشل و فريبنده اي
and age-appropriate.
تازه سنتم مناسبه
- What?
ي؟
- Oh, nothing.
اوه،هيي
- Look, you're getting wise.
ناه کنين،داري دانا ميشي
- I'm getting old.
دارم ير ميشم
- Not the same thing. I say you're getting wise.
اصلا شبيه هم نيستن من که ميم داري دانا ميشي
You worry about getting old?
ير شدن نرانت ميکنه؟
- I think being old's gonna be okay.
فکر کنم يريم واسه خودش خوبه
It's just the getting there that kicks your ass, you know?
فقط رسيدنه بهش که کونتو اره ميکنه،مييري؟
- You're gonna be a great old guy.
تو يه يرمرد فوق العاده ميشي
- Really? - Mm-hmm.
واقعا؟ اهم
- I feel like the nicest thing
فکر کنم اين قشن ترين يزي بود که
anyone's ever said to me.
يه نفر ممکن بهم فته باشه
Unless it's a criticism,
مر اينکه جنبه ي انتقادي داشت حرفت
like, "You're already judgmental and racist.
مثلا،تو همين الانشم زود قضاوت کن و نژادرست هستي
You're gonna be a great old guy."
تو يه يرمرد فوق العاده ميشي
- No, I mean you'll wear baggy pants,
نه منظورم اينه که شلوار کردي ميوشي
and you'll have a little belly,
بعد يه کويکم شيکم داري
And when you want more coffee, you'll say to the waitress,
و وقتيم بيشتر قهوه ميخواي به خدمتکارِ ميي
"Could you warm this up for me, dear?'
عزيز دلم ميشه اينو يه کم داغش کني برام؟
- You're right.
راست مييا
I will say that.
اينو ميم قشن
I think you're gonna be a great old person too.
فکر کنم توام يه ير خيلي خوبي ميشي
- Thanks'
مرسي
I want to be an old lady with long, gray hair in a ponytail.
ميخوام يه يرزن با موهاي بلند خاکستري دم اسبي باشم
- I can see it.
ميتونم ببينمش از الان
You're still foxy. You still got it.
هنوز واسه خودت جونوري هستي هنوز اون خو رو تو وجودت داري
That's what they're gonna 85”!' about you.
اين يزيه که همه درموردت بعدا مين
"She's still got it.“
هنوز اون روحيه رو داره
- They're saying it now.
همين الانشم مين
And I want a really, really wrinkly face.
دلم يه هره ي خيلي خيلي روکيده ام ميخواد
A small house, maybe by some water.
با يک خونه ي کويک،شايد کنار آب
I think getting old could be really nice.
فکر کنم ير شدنم ميتونه واسه خودش خوب باشه
# End of the day # # on the subway #
با تشکر از شما